Welcome to LiveOverflow.
Here you can find videos about computer internals,
with a focus on hacking and security concepts.
I also record myself solving hacking challenges
- it might be a bit boring to watch, but if
you always wondered how other people work
and think, it might be interesting for you.
Now let me tell you a short story about why
I am doing this here.
I was too young in the 90s and didn’t exist
in the 80s to be part of the seemingly golden
age of the hacker culture.
When I was a teenager I loved taking apart
electronics and looking at the green circuit
boards wondering with what kind of magic it
is imbued with.
Once my dad brought home our first computers
and we got access to the internet, I found
myself being fascinated with “hacking”
and wanted to learn more about it.
But all I found was crap, people trying to
sell old information or fake products.
So I never got into hacking until much later.
I started programming in Visual Basic and
made my first websites with html.
Eventually I moved on to php and other programming
languages.
Some years pass and I moved out to another
city to go to university.
One day I was sitting in front of my computer
coming across this hacking game by stripe.
A CTF where one level was to exploit a buffer
overflow.
I knew what a stack was.
And I was able to read simple assembler code
from university classes.
But not until I saw the shell popping up,
my mind being blown and struck in awe, I realized
I was at a position in life where I can pursue
a dream I had as a kid.
And I still wear the T-Shirt I got from the
stripe CTF with pride.
At the same time I had the opportunity to
join a hackerspace where I met so many intelligent
people and I went down a rabbit hole.
Not many years have passed since then.
And I still feel I have only explored a tiny
fraction of what is out there.
The content I am creating here is an attempt
to give anybody who want’s to understand
the world better, an opportunity to start
somewhere.
I want to give to others, what I wish I found
when I was a teenager sitting in the basement
typing into google “how to hack”.
At the same time I see more and more people
making tutorials on how to use certain hacking
tools, rather than explaining the underlying
concepts.
I understand that it looks cool, and that
you can feel very powerful.
But there is more to hacking than that.
Understanding concepts, understanding how
your phone and laptop do stuff, understanding
on a technical level how you are able to watch
this video right now.
That is amazing.
There is so much awesome stuff to discover
and break.
So I invite you to join me on this adventure
and “Hack the Planet!”.