This is the 10th episode.
And as you can see in the title, I am counting the episodes in hexadecimal.
我想知道谷歌的算法是否会用下一个视频来解决这个问题
is wrong.
无论如何，我想在这段视频中解释为什么十六进制很酷，以及为什么你应该使用
it, when it comes to computers.
I will also show you how I convert values back and forth and how I often work with them.
Ok.
So.
our computers work in binary, 0s and 1s.
因为它代表了我们电路的物理行为，我们有晶体管，
that are like switches and they are either turned on or off.
A single value that is either 0 or 1 is called a bit.
You may know that a byte is 8 bits.
But maybe you wonder why that is.
Well, this was not always the case.
Early computers might have had 6 bits per byte.
That we use 8 bits for a byte nowadays is just how history turned out.
It was IBMs fault with the System 360 that heavily pushed for an 8-bit byte.
Also some people say octad instead of byte to make clear that they mean 8 bit.
An interesting example is ascii, because you will notice that it actually only uses 7bit.
But because we now generally use 8bit bytes, we kind of waste the first bit.
We humans grew up with the decimal system.
We are used to counting with symbols from 0 to 9.
But that is rather arbitrary.
Sure, we have 10 fingers.
但是我们也可以用12分来计算，因为我们有12根手指骨，我们可以使用
thumb to point to which number we are at.
This is the Duodecimal system and we actually use it on our clock.
所以，如果你长大后用十六进制或二进制计数的话，你会觉得这很自然
to you.
Instead of thinking of numbers as something fixed, think of it as a tool.
And you can use whichever number system makes sense for a particular problem.
So our computers work with bits.
And for our modern computers we have defined that we generally work with bytes of 8 bits.
16位、32位或64位体系结构只需利用这个值，就可以很好地将其分割开来。
by 8.
当我们将数据看作原始位：0000 0000时，我们很快就会发现一个字节需要
space if we display it in that way.
Maybe decimal would be a cool representation.
It certainly would take less space to display them.
I will use python now to show you how we can convert binary to decimal numbers.
We simply say that this string represents a number in base 2.
Let’s do it for a couple of examples with a simple for loop.
Ok.
Well.
Takes less space.
Though, it kinda bothers me that the biggest value with 8 bits, is a weird number in decimal.
A number without any interesting properties or meanings.
Let’s have a look at those numbers in hex.
Hex numbers use symbols from 0-9 and A-F to describe a number.
We can extend our loop in python.
And now you can see how pretty hexadecimal numbers are to represent 8 bits.
最大的8位值也是十六进制的最大值，可以用两个表示
digits.
如果我们再加1个位，这样我们就有9个位，我们还必须再加一个
character.
不仅如此，如果你仔细观察，它也很好地代表了两个人
nibbles, that means 4 bits.
So a 8 bit number in hex can be represented by 2 symbols.
And each symbol refers to one nibble.
So this makes it very very clear and easy to read.
现在你可以理解为什么小数表示法不适合这个了
kind of stuff.
你能告诉我一个无符号32位整数所能代表的最大数是多少吗？
Well I don’t know in decimal.
I just know that 32bit is 4 times 8 bit and thus max int is 0xFFFFFFFF.
Now let me quickly show you some cool tricks with python to convert stuff back and forth.
Python has some builtin functions to convert numbers.
For example hex() and bin().
还可以使用int（）函数解析二进制或十六进制数，并指定哪个基数
it is.
如果您有一个二进制字符串，这意味着该字符串中的每个值可能不是
不错的ASCII可打印字符，您可以使用对字符串的编码和解码来获取
hex representation of the characters.
So hex 41 is a capital ‘A’ in ascii.
A much more powerful and important functionality is offered by python structs.
Which I use all the time when I deal with binary data.
First import struct.
And then we can use struct.unpack on our data.
In this case I define that this data is an unsigned Integer.
And you can see I can convert this binary data now to an integer number.
If you look closely you may wonder why the capital A seems to be at the end of the number.
The reason for that is that we have a little-endian system.
bit’s can be interpreted in two ways.
Either the first or the last bit can refer to the least-significant bit.
I think the picture on wikipedia makes this very clear.
当您从big endian系统接收数据时，这可能非常重要，因为
you have to be careful how you interpret this data.
但是使用python结构很容易，我们可以定义我们想要的endian系统
to interpret this data.
如果你看我的一些CTF开发挑战视频，你会看到我使用python结构
a lot.
Because it’s great to convert addresses and other data back and forth.
For example if we want to overwrite an address, we have to supply the data as a string.
So we can use struct.pack and pack a number as a binary string.
所以十六进制系统使得使用计算机变得更简单，你应该
get used to it.
But we just talked about positive numbers.
From 0 to 0xFF.
But how can we represent negative numbers.
也许你听过有符号的位，第一位告诉你它是不是负数
number or not.
不过，它并不像简单地读取剩余的7位并决定它是否为正那样简单。
or negative based on the first one.
-1 is actually 0xFF.
Well it does have the first bit set, but it’s not -127.
This wheel maybe makes it a bit more clear how negative numbers are actually interpreted.
将其绝对值转换为负值的操作，例如255
(0xFF) to -1 is called Two’s complement, you can read that on wikipedia.
And you can also very easily negate a given number by negating all bits and adding 1.
Many functions return -1 on error.
At first it sounds weird, but now you know that this is just all Fs.
So when you read data and you only get 1s (or Fs in hex) you might read an errror.
What about numbers with a fraction.
Well.
Don’t get me started on that.
It get’s really ugly.
但是你可以猜测，用逗号后面的许多数字表示一个值可以得到
very creative if you have only 0s and 1s.
现在，在我们结束之前，让我们总结一下术语：
we start with a bit.
0 or 1.
4 bits are a nibble.
8 bits are a byte.
And in hexadecimal we can represent a byte with two digits.
on 32bit architecture a word refers to 32bit or 4 bytes.
But on 64bit architecture a word is 64bit, or 8 bytes.
And a double word is obviously the double amount of that.
As you can see, a computer only has bits.
And how we deal with those bits is up to our interpretation.
我知道这是一个有点短和技术含量较低的视频，但我认为它适合下次
we will dive deep and exploit our first buffer overflow.