In this episode we start to get a little bit closer to a full buffer overflow.
在上一集中，我们学习了缓冲区溢出如何改变局部变量，
which are stored on the stack.
Now we will have a look at stack level 3, which is very similar.
If you forgot how we were able to solve stack level 0, you should go back and watch it again.
When we look at this code, we see that it is basically the same.
唯一的区别是名称，而不是修改过的变量，我们有fp变量，
which is defined as a function pointer.
语法看起来有点难看，但是如果检查if大小写，它只检查fp是否不是。
zero, and then just calls fp, as if it were a function.
Now you know that a function has an address location in memory.
So it will basically call whatever address is stored in fp.
现在像stack0中的修改变量一样，函数指针fp被设置为0，并且
after the gets function it will be checked if it’s not zero anymore.
So we know that fp must also be stored on the stack.
提示是，我们可以使用gdb或objhump来确定win（）函数的位置。
lies in memory.
So first let’s use gdb and you can use examine or print to get the address of win.
Then set the disassembly flavor to intel and disassemble main.
Exactly like stack0, we can see that it makes space for hex 60 bytes on the stack.
Then we set esp offset 5c to 0, so that is the location of the fp variable.
在gets之后，我们比较值，如果它仍然是0，如果不是，
we load the value into eax down here, and call that address.
So let’s set a breakpoint at this call.
Now execute it and enter enough characters to overwrite this value on the stack.
Exactly like last video.
好的，我们点击断点，让我们看看寄存器，我们可以看到
succesfully set eax to 41414141, which is the ascii value of capital A.
And the next instruction tries to call this address.
So basically jump there.
But that is obviously invalid memory, se we get a Segmentation fault.
Now open a second ssh session.
And create a python script, that will be our exploit.
So let’s first try to figure out which offset controls eax.
So simply print a recognizable pattern.
For example the alphabet.
Ok. cool.
So pipe this output in a file.
Now you can use this file in gdb as input.
So we dont have to type it everytime, it will use the content of that file as input.
现在“运行”并使用左箭头重定向标准输入中的文件内容
the program.
Ok so eax it’s hex 51, and that is a capital Q.
So now we know which offset modifies eax.
let’s rewrite the code a little bit.
Let’s call this part up to the “Qs” - padding.
So now we want to write here the address of the win function.
So simply use backslash x as hex escape for those byte values.
Oh oops.
That doesn fit.
There is a leading 0 missing.
Save, write the file.
And check it in gdb.
嗯？
分离故障？
The address looks a bit weird.
看来是走错了路？
Well, that is because of the endianess.
So the numerical value will be basically the other way around.
cool.
Eax looks fine now.
让我们继续，我们成功地更改了代码流！
Now let’s quickly solve the next level as well.
This level is our first buffer overflow, where we take advantage of the stack layout.
The code doesn’t contain much.
There is no function pointer variable we could overwrite.
And now modified variable.
But it still wants us to execute win.
那我们该怎么做呢？
现在你还记得上一个视频中的堆栈是什么样子的吗？
下面是一个简短的概括：
So here on the left you can see the assembler code.
在右边，我将展示这个堆栈。使用3个重要寄存器，指令
pointer EIP, the stack pointer ESP and the base pointer EBP.
So first it starts somewhere else with a ‘call main’.
Call will push the theoretically next instruction pointer onto the stack.
And then jump to our main function.
如您所见，当按下下一条指令的地址时，堆栈指针
got incremented and the address placed there.
So now comes our push EBP.
我们现在怎么知道从梅因返回哪里？
Well if you remember, call pushed the address of the instruction after the call.
So the next value on the stack is where we want to return to.
ret指令基本上就是把这个地址输入指令
pointer.
And thus jumping back where we came from.
如你所见，当一个函数被调用时，我们想要返回的地址，将
be stored on the stack.
因此，我们可以简单地溢出返回指针，而不是溢出局部变量
on the stack.
And when main would return, it would read the wrong value and jump there instead.
So let’s use the code that we have just written, and modify it a bit.
Let’s make the payload a bit longer and simply throw it at this program in gdb.
Segmentationfault in hex 54, so we succsefully redirected code execution, to bad memory.
And if you look closely you can also spot that the basepointer is hex 53.
所以那个也被覆盖了，因为如果你记得上一个视频，旧的basepointer
is also stored on the stack, right before the instruction pointer.
And hex 54 is T. So T allows us to control the instruction pointer.
This time let’s use objdump to find the address of the win function.
With -t we get all symbols, and then we can grep for win.
So there is our address.
Now let’s modify our exploit code.
Let’s remove everything up to the S, because that is the base pointer.
Now create two variables ebp and eip.
We don’t care about EBP so we can just set it to whatever we want.
And next we want to set the instruction pointer.
But let me show a better way to encode the address as a string.
So import struct.
然后可以使用struct.pack将地址从整数转换为
binary string.
Then print the padding and append the ebp and eip variable.
so let’s execute this exploit and pipe it into the stack4 level.
代码流已成功更改！
Amazing.
We smashed the stack and controlled the instruction pointer.
但你还是会有分离的错误吗？
原因是，在Win函数完成后，它试图返回到
堆栈上的下一个值，现在有些乱七八糟，可能不在有效的
code area.
So it will crash eventually.
But we don’t care, because we executed what we wanted.
在下一个视频中，我们将用shellcode编写第一个缓冲区溢出，它将
show you how powerful a buffer overflow can be.
And it will be our first exploit that will get us root privileges.