Let’s move on to exploit-exercises stack level 5.
You should have watched the previous videos to understand how we got here.
挑战描述说
Stack5 is a standard buffer overflow, this time introducing shellcode.
提示是：
that, it might be easier to use someone elses shellcode.
That is also what we will do.
和
如果调试shellcode，请使用操作码hex cc的“int3”指令停止
the program executing and return to the debugger.
And that is very helpful.
Ok, let’s have a look at this code.
It is surprisingly small.
只有一个函数调用gets（），我们知道它允许我们覆盖数据
on the stack.
那么，我们如何从没有程序功能的地方得到一个根shell呢？
So put on your wizard's hat, because we will do some magic.
Let’s open this program in gdb, and let’s just throw a long string against it.
To do that let’s already prepare our exploit script.
So first we want to find the offset that allows us to control the instruction pointer.
I’d like to use a simple pattern like the alphabet.
So I create this exploit variable and assign the long string to it, and then print that.
现在将该脚本的输出重定向到一个文件中，然后我们可以将该文件用作
gdb.
Before we execute the program, let’s create a breakpoint at the return of main.
And let’s define a hook, like we have done in a previous video.
定义钩子停止，我们希望显示将执行的当前指令
next, so examine one instruction at the location of eip.
And then examine 8 words as hex from the stack.
And end.
Then execute it, and we hit the breakpoint at the return.
The next line shows us how the stack looks like right now.
And when we execute the ret, we will jump to the address that was on the stack before.
So no execute it again with the alphabet.
We are at the return again, and we can see that we have overwritten stuff on the stack.
So now we try to return to address hex 54545454.
Which is obviously invalid, so we get a Segmentation Fault.
使用examine作为字符串，我们可以看到我们已经用
T’s.
So let’s update our exploit script.
This will be our padding.
然后我们创建变量eip，我们可以使用它来控制指令指针和
jump anywhere we want.
And I use struct to create a binary string from the address again.
So struct.pack.
但是我们想跳到哪里呢？
We don’t have any win() function like in previous levels.
你知道我们可以跳到哪里吗？
I think I will give you a second to think about this.
Right, we can just jump to the stack where we control data.
So obviously we could place some assembler code there.
Now let’s find a good address.
We could just jump right after the instruction pointer we control.
To do that just run again, execute the ret and have a look at the stack pointer.
So that is the address we want to jump to.
现在我们必须在返回指针之后附加要执行的代码，所以为什么
not use the opcode CC, the int3, they were suggesting in the challenge description.
Let’s also quickly have a look at the intel instruction reference.
Let’s search for “Int 3”.
Ok mmhh… call itnerrupt procedure.
what else do we find.
在这个关于一般异常的表中，它调用这个指令断点？
Huuu, that’s interesting.
Ok and here is the description of it.
Interrupt number 3, traps to debugger.
下面是：
Int3指令是一个特殊的单字节操作码（CC），用于调用
debug exception handler.
（此单字节格式很有价值，因为它可以用来替换
具有断点的指令，包括其他单字节指令，但不过度写入
other code).
wooooh.
那是什么意思？
嗯，你认为gdb是如何工作的？
或者其他的调试器？
How can you just stop the CPU from executing something.
或者只是一个指令？
Actually a debugger can just use the INT 3 instruction.
Let’s make an example.
We just created a breakpoint at this ret.
What we actually did was, we replaced this return instruction in memory with int 3.
And when the CPU reached this instruction, an exception was raised.
或者在硬件方面，一个中断被触发，从而使CPU停止继续执行。
并调用一个中断处理程序（类似于系统调用如何导致中断和执行
continued somewhere else).
And we can now decide how we want to handle this exception.
如果我们是一个调试器，现在我们将用原来的指令替换这个int 3指令。
value, the return instruction.
That can also be used as an anti reversing technique.
Because a regular application will not use the CC instruction.
因此，恶意软件可能会不断扫描自己的CC操作码，如果它找到了，它
knows that somebody attached a debugger and tried to set a breakpoint.
And now we will use the CC in our payload.
So let’s append a couple of CCs after the overwritten return pointer.
Don’t forget to write the output of the script into the exploit file.
And then test this in gdb.
Ok run again.
We can see that we stopped at the ret and we see the address where we would return to.
当我们现在继续时，我们从堆栈中弹出指令指针值，从而继续
在堆栈上执行，我们有int 3指令，如您所见，gdb
stopped because it received a signal SIGTRAP, a trace/breakpoint trap.
Cool.
这样我们就知道我们有代码执行，因为我们成功地注入了一个汇编程序
instruction.
现在，没有gdb这也行吗？
让我们试试……
但是我们得到了非法指令？
That is not what we should see.
We should get the breakpoint message.
Let’s open it in gdb here and try it again.
Still illegal instruction.
Let’s set the hooks and the breakpoints like in the other gdb session.
Ok run.
嗯…
The addresses on the stack are not the same.
为什么它们不同？
Let’s do something crazy.
Print the whole stack.
I just print a thousand strings or something.
Let’s se what we get.
Ok first we have some gibebrish.
Let’s go further.
UUUh… see.
Now we get some interesting stuff.
Let’s do the same in the other gdb session.
This looks like the environment variables.
例如，这里是我们在以前的编程中使用的用户环境变量
video.
Mh and when you look at the addresses, they are still diferent.
So let’s look a bit further down.
mh! down here they are the same.
So between here and the environemnt variables above there mus be something different.
当你仔细观察，你可以看到pwd环境变量，当前
working directory is different.
They have a different length.
所以很明显，一个执行环境需要在堆栈上有更多的空间来存储这个
path.
And thus pushing the stack further up.
No wonder that the stack addresses are not the same anymore.
那么我们如何应对呢？
您可以使用一些技术来更好地控制
stack.
For example by removing all environment variables before executing a binary.
But there is another very easy but effective trick.
这里有一个提示：
不，不，不，不，不，不
好的……没有幻灯片……
Let’s just add a looooot of NOP instructions.
A Nop instruction performs no operation.
And it has the opcode hex 90.
而不是选择一个非常具体的堆栈地址，让我们选择一个我们希望
hits our nops.
So run again.
Now we can see we have a lot of NOPs on the stack.
And the address we will jump to points somewhere else further down.
如果我们看更多的堆栈，我们可以看到它几乎就在中间。
of the nops.
So let’s just single step forwards.
现在我们高兴地滑下NOP滑道，直到我们用陷阱到达底部！
Boom.
Cool.
And that also works now outside of gdb.
Now instead of CC, we want to execute something useful.
So let’s look for some shellcode.
As the challenge description said, it’s best to reuse shellcode from other people.
I really like the collection of shellcode from shellstorm.
Shellstorm has a lot of different kind of shellcode, for a lot of different system.
So we are looking for a Linux Intel 32bit shellcode.
FreeBSD, Linux on ARM, 64bit, and here we have 32bit.
They all have a short description and do different stuff.
But we are looking for a simple execve that will execute a shell.
So, why not take this one.
如果你看一下汇编程序代码，它所做的基本上就是推送一些值
on the stack, which are infact just a string that is the path /bin/sh.
And then calls execve.
将字节作为有效负载复制到python exploit脚本中，我们可以将其与
program.
mhmh… nothing happens.
它不工作吗？
Let’s add the CC at the start of the payload if we still hit it.
It should work.
Remove the CC againa and try it in gdb. let’s single step.
We are sliding down the nop slide.
All seems fine.
And now comes the shellcode.
And it says: “Executing new program, /bin/dash”.
That first sounds weird, but is correct.
/bin/sh just points to /bin/dash.
为什么它不起作用？
Also on a side note.
This gdb session is no broken.
Because execve, replaces the current program with another one.
So stack5 got replaced by /bin/dash.
And you can see that when you try to execute it again.
So you would have to load stack5 again with file.
Ok.
那么问题是什么呢？
This is one of the things I got nuts.
When I first got stuck like this I spend houuurs trying to figure out what is happening.
As much as I want to see anybody else suffer like me, I tell you what the problem is.
你执行的shell需要一些输入，对吗？
From standard input.
But!.
We used a program and redirected it’s stdoutput into the stdinput of this program.
And when the program was done it closed that pipe.
So now the shell is executed, but doesn’t have any input.
Because it’s closed.
So it will just exit.
And there is a neat trick to get basically around that.
When you use cat without parameters, it simply redirect it’s stdinput to the standard output.
See like here.
You type something in, and it get’s reflected out.
Now you can chain programs together on one line, for example with semicolon.
所以我们可以先打印漏洞的输出，然后执行cat，这样我们就可以
enter new input.
如果我们现在用一些括号将其分组，并将它们的组合输出重定向到
堆栈级别，漏洞首先运行并执行shell，然后cat将接管
and we can simply relay input via cat to the shell.
BAM! it works.
We have an ugly shell, and we can verify our identity with whoami, or id.
So now we escalated privileges to root.
Damn. feels so good.
It’s just beautiful.