在上一集中，我们通过覆盖
堆栈上的返回指针并跳转到我们放置在堆栈上的shellcode
as well.
在本集中，我们将查看第6层堆栈，它将查看当您
restrictions on the return address.
要理解此视频，您必须了解正常缓冲区溢出和跳至
shellcode works.
I hope I explained it well enough in the past videos.
But if there are still open questions, please post them on reddit.
I really need you to have understood that stuff.
作为提示，这个水平告诉我们，
这个级别可以用两种方法完成，例如查找有效负载的副本
(objdump -s), or ret2libc, or even return orientated programming.
In this video we will not be able to explore return oriented programming.
但是我会给你看一些其他的技巧，最终会导致回归导向
programming.
So let’s have a look at the source code.
And again, it’s very similar to the previous levels, just some small changes.
Instead of everything being in main, main calls this function get_path.
Get path allocates a string buffer for 64 characters.
Then reads a string with gets.
我们现在都知道，用get我们可以任意地读许多字符，我们
can use to overwrite the return pointer on the stack.
But the next line is interesting.
_ builtin返回地址是编译器中的一个函数，您可以使用它来读取
current return address from the stack.
And this return address is checked if it starts with hex 0xbf.
The ampersand performs a bitwise AND with the address.
After that only the part where they were same survives.
basically setting the remaining bits to 0.
And checking if the front is still hex bf.
If the return address starts with 0xbf, it prints this return address and exits.
When we use our exploit from last time.
并调整填充以解释这个函数中新的无符号int，我们看到
that it doesn’t work.
It fails with bzzzt.
Ok.
So we cannot use addresses that start with hex bf.
The exit protects this function from being exploited that way.
Because the exit is a syscall that simply quits the program.
So even though we have smashed the return pointer, this function will never return.
所以你可以看到，即使有一个缓冲区溢出也不一定意味着你可以
exploit it.
当我们现在在gdb中打开这个级别时，在getpath处中断，运行它，然后查看映射的
memory with `info proc map`.
We can see that the only addresses that start with bf are on the stack.
So basically we cannot return to a stack address.
这太疯狂了，如果我们不能返回到堆栈中
放置我们的代码？
So first of all, we can still control the return pointer.
As long as it doesn’t start with bf.
And now comes this sick idea, of returning into known code.
Let’s think about this.
返回指令只查看堆栈顶部的当前地址，将其移除，然后
just jumps there.
… What would happen if you return to the address 0x080484f9.
Which is the return instruction itself.
Think about this.
We overwrite the return pointer with hex 0x080.
We reach the return instruction, it will pop this address from the stack and jump to it.
Basically just jump to itself.
And now it will read the next address on the stack and jump there.
Now you could repeat that.
Make the next address on the stack again 0x080.
Or place the address of the stack here.
And we can return into the stack again.
And in theory that should work.
Because the original return address got overwritten with an address that starts with 0x080.
Ok let’s try that.
let’s modify our exploit code.
Instead of the shellcode let’s use int 3, CC instruction again.
For a trap.
我们现在都知道，当我们攻击它们时，我们有代码执行，我们只需要找到
suitable shellcode.
So let’s focus on the interesting part.
Set a breakpoint at the return of getpath, and then run it with our exploit input.
We hit the breakpoint.
And we got past the return pointer check.
So let’s look at the stack ourselves.
We can see that the address on top of the stack is now the 0x080.
Which is the return instruction.
So now single step forward.
This should pop this address from the stack and jump there.
And indeed.
We hit the breakpoint again, because we jumped to itself.
When you now look at the stack, the next address on the stack is the stack address.
And we will return into this address now.
因此，当我们继续时，我们将返回到堆栈中，就像在前面的漏洞中一样，
we hit our traps.
繁荣！
任意代码执行！
By the way.
This address where we jumped to, the 0x080 is a gadget.
When you read about return oriented programming, you are looking for gadgets.
And that was a simple no operation gadget.
It was just a return, doing nothing.
对于全回报导向的编程，你会寻找能做更多事情的小工具，
before returning to the next address.
Now when we do this kind of stuff, you hear me saying “return into”, or “jump to”.
Those become equivalent in this case.
因为是的，我们执行一个返回指令，但不返回到原始函数
anymore.
We are returning into something else.
Effectively just jumping somewhere else.
So I hope that doesn’t confuse you.
Let’s have a look at another trick.
It’s very similar to what we did in stack level 4.
So where else could we jump to.
其中之一
hints said we could look into ret2libc.
Now that you are almost a pro in exploitation, you understand what that means.
Return into libc.
Like we just returned into some code, we could also return into the huge library libc.
There must be something interesting that we could abuse.
One interesting function from libc is system.
Which executes a shell command.
With print system, we can find the address of it.
But simply returning into it will probably not work.
We need to make sure to control a couple of things.
Let’s create a simple C program that calls the libc system for us.
In the end we want to somehow execute system with /bin/sh.
Because then we get a shell.
If we try that here, that works well.
Now let’s look at this in gdb.
我们可以看到，在调用系统之前，我们要执行的命令的地址
is put on top of the stack.
如我们所知，对函数的调用将把返回地址作为
well.
因此，如果我们画出这个，这就是当我们开始时堆栈的样子。
system.
First the address of the command is placed on the stack.
And then the address we want to return to.
Now imagine if we use our buffer overflow to return into system.
Firstof all we didn’t execute a call instruction.
Thus there was no return address pushed.
But we fully control the stack.
So system expects the stack to look like this.
我们可以手工建造！
So first we have to put the return address for system on the stack.
But actually we don’t care about this right now.
But that is still cool and important, and remember that.
Because you can chain those things together.
就像我们以前一个接一个地链接了两个返回，我们可以链接多个函数调用
或其他小工具，通过始终控制下一个的返回指针
step.
所以在我们的例子中，当系统完成时，我们会遇到一个segfault，因为它会返回
into 0x41414141.
the next address on the stack has to be a string we want to execute.
Preferably “/bin/sh”.
There are many options how to get a reference to such a string.
one option would be to use a stack address.
Because there are strings we control.
Or environment variables.
Because they are at the bottom of the stack and a bit easier to predict.
But as you remember, the stack is a bit unreliable and shifting around.
A more reliable technique is this here.
We can use find to search in the mapped memory of libc for a string.
Cool, apparently at this address we can find /bin/sh.
Let’s check if that is true.
Examine memory as string at this address.
令人惊叹的！
What the frak! gdb.
What the hell are you doing.
你为什么说你在那里找到了垃圾桶，如果没有呢？
I have no idea why this happens.
Couldn’t find anything online.
Anyway.
Ignore this.
Here is another technique.
We can use strings to find all strings in libc.
And with -t we can print the offset inside this file as hex.
And then we can simply add this offset to the address libc is loaded to.
And that is the real address of /bin/sh.
Ok so let’s copy this address into our exploit.
And then let’s try it.
Remember to use the trick from the previous video with the parenthesis and cat.
Because the exploit script will close the input again.
酷！
It works.
What we just did was the technique called ret2libc.
我们从未在堆栈上执行过任何代码！
Maybe you ask yourself why the hell the stack was executable in the first place.
There is no valid reason why the stack should be executable.
That’s why there exists a general memory policy nowadays.
Write xor Execute.
Basically it means, never have a memory page that is writeable AND executable.
因为这样攻击者就不能执行他能够在
process memory.
因此，我们希望今天每个现代系统都使用DEP、数据执行预防和集合
the NX bit, the non executable bit for memory pages like the stack.
But reality is not so simple.
随着物联网的兴起，嵌入式设备也在兴起，但它们通常不会
support features like that.
Or modern programming languages like javascript use JIT.
Just in time compiler.
So they have to compile code on the fly in memory when needed and execute that.
So they need writeable and executable memory regions.
但是，即使我们有DEP，我们也可以使用像ret2libc这样的技术来从不执行实际的shellcode，
but still pwn a system.
And at some point in the future, I will make a video about return oriented programming.
Which is the next advanced step for this kind of technique.