我们已经看过很多集了，我们阅读汇编代码和逆向工程。
how a program works.
我们甚至通过使用缓冲区溢出漏洞在
一个用C语言写的节目。在这一集里，我想向你展示
can learn how to read assembler produced by C code yourself.
The idea is simple.
只需编写一些具有不同C语言特性的C代码，然后查看汇编程序代码
that is produced by compiling it.
This is often part of normal research.
例如，听谷歌零号项目的伊恩·比尔在一次关于他的谈话中所说的话。
research on Inter Process Calls on OSX.
要想扭转局面，或者理解这类事情是如何运作的，一个方法就是坐着
在IDA中，只需反转序列化和反序列化代码，然后慢慢构建
up a picture of how it works.
但另一种很好的方法是，编写一个测试程序来发送
messages and then find the right place using lldb to break and just start dumping hex.
因此，由于他必须理解相当复杂的数据结构，他只需编写一个
test program to analyse it, instead of reversing a full application.
或者是在2007从黑头美国的一篇关于如何逆转C++程序的演讲和论文，
by looking at C++ concepts and how they look like in assembler.
所以现在我已经创建了三个不同的C代码测试用例，您可以在我的Github中找到它们。
repository, or just write it yourself.
One is about variables and datatypes.
One is about function calls.
And one is about control flow stuff like loops and ifs.
So let’s start with the variables.c.
First thing I want to point out are those triple Xs.
Those triple Xs are defined as an assembler NOP instruction.
原因是，稍后当我们研究拆卸时，我们可以找到那些NOP
which are separating our tests, and that is pretty neat.
所以这使得我们更容易看到C代码的哪一行负责其中的哪一行
assembler.
I will not go over every single test, this is something you could do yourself.
Simply pause the video at certain points or clone the repository.
Anyway.
Let’s get started.
First of all you can see here a couple of simple numbers.
First we define a couple of numbers.
Unsigned and signed, integers and floating numbers.
And different sizes with uint32 or uint64.
后者很重要，因为正整数的大小取决于32位
or 64bit, so it can lead to bugs.
So better use datatypes you are guaranteed to get a certain size.
如果你想进一步了解如何正确地编程C，有一个很棒的博客条目叫做
“How to C in 2015”.
然后我们创建一个包含32位无符号整数的数组，并访问其中的一个元素
array.
Then we look at a single character.
And then also a string.
也许你知道星星*在c中的意思是“指针”，所以我们定义了一个指向
to a string.
我添加了一个makefile，所以您可以简单地在终端中键入'make'来编译所有
files.
Or make clean to remove the binaries.
This will create a 32bit and a 64bit version of the variables program.
但是正如你所看到的，我在编译32位版本时遇到了一个错误，其中包含了-m32
64bit machine.
So I have to install the 32bit libraries first, to be able to build the code.
After installing those, the build works fine.
A Makefile is just a little script that defines how a project has to be compiled.
那么让我们打开gdb中彼此相邻的代码、32位和64位版本并反汇编
main.
And also open the code.
好了，现在让我们来看第一个带负值、有符号和无符号的整数示例。
values.
首先，所有这些局部变量都存储在堆栈的某个地方，您可以看到
that because they are referenced relative to the base-pointer.
Then you notice that the assembler code doesn’t know negative numbers.
They are fff something.
如果你对负数的显示方式感兴趣，请看我的第10集
numbers.
And also there is no difference between variables that are signed or unsigned.
But there is one difference between the 32bit and the 64bit code.
因为我们定义了一个64位长的数字，但是32位的寄存器只有
32bit.
So if you want to write full 64bit, you have to write two times.
The floating point numbers are also interesting.
Because they got stored somewhere else in the program.
And that value is then moved into the local variable.
The array is also interesting.
We created an array with 10 values but only set the first 5 values to a default value.
As you can see those values are stored on the stack.
And then it is moved from that location on the stack to the real array location.
Instead of writing it directly to the array it does it this way.
No idea why.
And you can see down here when we reference the 3rd entry.
So you can see that this is the real location of the array on the stack.
Next come the strings.
You can see that a character is just a byte.
It doesn’t matter if we have an unsigned int with 8bit or a char.
It’s the same.
And strings are also referenced over an address.
So the local variable is not an array of charactes.
the local variable contains an address pointing to a string.
Now let’s have a look at the control_flows.
Open it in radare.
Analyse all, seek to main function and enter Visual mode.
First we set a variable to zero.
And then comes the if.
This is done by loading this local variable in a register and comparing to hex ff.
And then jump if it was less or equal.
So you can see which branch it may take.
Then comes a while loop.
我们在寄存器中再次加载局部变量，将其与一个值进行比较，然后跳进去
the block or leave.
And inside the block we load this value again, increment it and write it back.
Now compare it to the foor loop.
基本上是一样的！
We start by setting the variable to 0.
Then we compare if the loop condition is still true.
And inside the loop block, we can see our NOP.
And at the end of the block we increment the variable by 1.
Exactly the same like the while loop.
So you can see that a for and a while loop in C are basically the same.
Next let’s have a look at how functions are called.
Again open both the 32bit and 64bit version.
First thing you notice that the 64bit version moves a 0 in eax.
No idea why.
Otherwise the function call looks the same.
Except look at the addresses.
If you have no ASLR, then 64bit code is generally at hex 40 something.
While 32bit code is at hex 80 something.
知道这样的东西是有帮助的，因为如果你看到一个地址有40多岁，你
know immediately that it’s pointing into your code.
So the next function returns a value and we save it in a variable.
And you can see that in both cases, the value is taken from the eax register.
Ok, so apparently return values are handled via eax.
Now function 3 is interesting, because we pass a parameter to it.
在32位中，您可以看到该值是从某个位置加载的，然后存储在
stack.
And then the function is called.
But on 64bit we see that the value is loaded into the edi register.
This is our first big difference.
64位中的函数似乎是用寄存器中的参数调用的，而32位中的
parameters are stored on the stack.
Next function uses 2 parameters.
And again, you can see how 32bit just places the value on the stack.
First parameter on top of the stack, the second a bit further down.
But in 64bit you can see that it uses esi and edi for that.
Now we get curious.
当我们有这么多参数，我们不能将它们全部保存在寄存器中时，64位会做什么？
First of all 32bit code again.
You can see how the parameters are stored on the stack.
And the first parameter is on top of the stack, and the last value moved.
That’s what we would expect.
在64位中，我们可以看到前两个参数存储在寄存器edi中，
esi, edx, and so forth.
But from the 7th parameter on, they get stored on the stack as well.
令人惊叹的！
Now you can identify all kind of different assembler patterns.
You don’t need a decompiler all the time.
You can do this all in your head.
当你逆转越来越多的程序时，这些模式变得更容易识别，
and you will not feel overwhelmed again with the mass of weird instructions.
You will be able to scan over a function and say: “ah here is a local variable.
Then calls this other function with this variable as parameter.
And the return value is used in a loop”.
你可以用同样的方法来理解不同的拆卸器，比如Hopper，Radare，
gdb display code.
Or for example how different the at&amp;t assembler syntax is from the intel syntax.
I hope you have a lot of fun next time reversing a program.