两集前，我们第一次利用格式字符串，在最后一段视频中，我们看了一下
关于如何动态地将库链接到二进制文件-基本上，程序如何
call functions from libc.
And we also had an idea how to abuse this, when we want to redirect code execution.
在本视频中，我们将使用此技术从漏洞攻击练习中利用格式级别4
protostar.
First let’s have a look at the code.
The main function calls vuln.
Vuln reads up to 512 characters from standard input into the buffer.
And then uses printf to print the buffer.
我们还立即看到缓冲区是printf-的第一个参数。
that is the format parameter.
After the printf there is a call to exit().
This means that this function vuln will never return.
It will perform the syscall exit to the kernel, which will quit this process.
所以如果我们覆盖这个函数的返回指针，我们将永远不会返回
we could not exploit it.
因此，我们使用上一个视频中的技术覆盖get entry for exit，使用
the address for hello.
That instead of exit we execute hello at the end.
Let’s get everything ready.
I use again vmware to run the protostar image and connect to it via ssh with putty.
Open one window for the binary.
And another window where we can write the exploit.
我们也可能希望立即导入结构模块，因为我们需要它来转换
integers to binary strings.
Let’s start by first verifying that we have a format string vulnerability.
We can just specify some format characters and see if they are turned into numbers.
是的！
That works.
So to make this exploit work we have to figure out a few addresses.
Let’s get the address of the hello function with “x” examine hello.
Here it is.
Let’s copy that into our exploit script.
只需突出显示要复制的区域，然后执行
a mouse right click in the other window.
接下来，让我们试着找到全局偏移量表，我们要在其中写入这个hello地址。
to.
Disassemble main.
Ok.
Right.
I forgot.
We call vuln.
So disassemble vuln.
And at the bottom you can see the call to exit at the procedure linkage table ptl.
拆下那个地址，我们现在可以看到第一个引用的地址
instruction with the jump.
That tries to reference the address of exit from glibc from there.
So examine that address.
And yup.
That’s the global offset table.
Now we also store that table address in our script.
Now let’s set two breakpoints in vuln.
One before the printf.
And one after the printf.
Next let’s simulate by hand overwriting the got entry.
So we run the code.
在printf中，我们将global offset表中的exit条目更改为hello和
continue to execute the exit at the end of vuln.
Run. we enter some random input.
First breakpoint.
Now we are befoire the printf.
Now let’s overwrite the GOT entry.
Let’s check GOTagain.
现在，用大括号int编写一个地址集，然后写入
want to write.
And now the entry for exit in the got has changed.
Continue once.
Now we are after the porintf.
Just one instruction away from the call to exit.
Next instruction.
And disassemble and info registers.
Yup, we are at the exit.
So let’s continue and see if we execute exit, or hello.
Whoop.
Ok. we executed hello.
That worked.
Now we just have to achieve this write with a format string and percentage n.
Ok.
Step one.
让我们退出调试器，通过播放找到堆栈中输入的字符串
around with the format specifiers.
We use our script to do those tests.
So first we know the buffer is 512 bytes long.
So let’s write a function that pads our string to that length.
所以我们只需在字符串中附加一定数量的字符，其中该数字为512减去
the length of the current string.
Then we create a variable exploit and print that variable padded.
当我们执行它时，我们可以看到我们的漏洞字符串，它被填充到512
characters.
So this will print the first 4 values from the stack.
Yup seems to work.
现在，让我们在字符串前面加上一些可识别的字符，然后尝试看看有多远
away our string is on the stack.
哈！
Cool.
Ok.
Our string already starts with the 4th value.
现在我们可以使用格式字符串中的数字美元符号来具体引用
that offset.
So 4 dollar after the percentage sign.
这将尝试引用printf的第4个参数，而不是遍历这些参数
one after another.
See, now all values are 41414141.
我希望你记得百分比n可以用来写印刷字符数
to an address on the stack.
所以我们可以用全局偏移表地址替换a字符
to write to that value.
Let’s try it.
We use struct to convert the integer address to a binary string.
Struct.
Pack.
I. exit_plt.
Yup, we seem to hit that address.
Let’s replace the percentage x with percentage n and see what that does in gdb.
But first write the output of this script to a file so we can use it in gdb as input.
Don’t forget to set the breakpoints again.
Run and pipe in the exploit string.
And we hit the breakpoint.
So now we are about to execute the printf.
Let’s check the GOT entry.
Now let’s execute the printf and let’s check again.
哈！
We have overwritten GOT. with a fairly small number.
If we now continue we will segfault in exit, because at this address is no function.
因此，百分比n成功地将打印到GOT中的字符数写入
table.
现在我们所要做的就是把字符打印出来，这样我们就能找到地址
of hello.
Mhmh… hex 0x80484b4.
Damn… that’s a big number.
We have to print like over 134 MILLIOPn characters.
每个字符都是一个字节，所以我们必须像128兆字节一样打印文本？
这样行吗？
Well, first of all we only have space for 512 characters in the buffer.
So we can’t simply write them all.
But we can abuse printf format strings again to pad an output string to any size.
Which allows us to write way more characters.
Let’s try that.
Let’s also change the number of ns down to only one.
啊。事实上，我们把它改回x，这样我们就不会一直砸桌子了。
we can make sure we always hit the address.
So let’s pad this to to like 30 characters, to see if that works.
哦，我们不能忘了在后面再加一个%x，稍后我们将用它替换
percentage n.
Run it against the format4 binary.
And yes.
See all those spaces.
Text got padded to 30 characters.
Now le’ts try that with 134 million.
Okay. seems to work.
It’s printing and printing and printing.
All those millions of spaces.
This taks aaaages.
And we arrived at the end.
Let’s try that in gdb again with percentage n.
Urgh man.
这需要很长时间…
:( Printing those hundret megabytes is just crazy.
But it did change the global offset table pretty close to hello.
We just would have to fiddle around a bit and adjust it exactly.
但你知道吗？
This sucks to print so many characters.
Let’s use a little trick.
Let’s use TWO shorter writes to achieve the same.
我们可以先用一个小得多的值写下下面的两个字节，
然后在地址+2处执行另一个写入操作，将另一个较小的值写入较高的值。
bytes.
Thus constructing the whole 4 byte through two writes.
So let’s try to write the lower two bytes first.
Let’s start with a padding like 30.
Write the output again into the file.
And run gdb with it as input.
Ok, so with the padding of 30 we were able to write hex 2e, which is 46.
Our goal is to write the two lower bytes so we want 84b4, which is 33972.
因为我们有30个填充物，但最终我们只有46个，我们必须补偿16个填充物。
characters.
So we substract 16 from it, so we want to put 33960 as a padding.
当我们运行它并查看got条目时，我们可以确认下面两个字节是
now 84b4.
Now to address the two higher bytes we move our address by two forward.
And perform another write.
So let’s add this address as well.
So EXIT_PLT plus 2.
This means that for the second write we want to address the fith element on the stack.
And now we just have to figure out how many we need to write here.
Let’s try with 30 again.
Ok.
The lower two bytes now stay 84b4.
Perfect.
And the higher bytes are 84d2.
But we want to get 0804.
那么，如果我们只能增加字符的数量，我们如何才能得到一个更低的数字呢？
实际上，我们不只是写两个字节，我们总是写四个字节，这意味着
that also currently we screw up data that is stored behind our exit GOT entry.
现在猜猜，如果我们写的足够多以至于第3个字节
is 1 and the rest becomes 0 again.
It doesn’t matter for the GOT, because it will only see the other 4 bytes.
So basically we overflow those two upper bytes so we can get there a lower value in.
Now currently we have 84d2.
And we want 0804.
I mean.
We actually want 10804.
如果我们现在把84d2从这里减去，我们知道我们应该写多少得到
10804.
So 8332.
But that’s hex, so that is 33586.
And it already included the 30 padding.
So we must not forget that.
Now we might be done.
Let’s check.
We write the output file.
We run gdb.
We break before the printf.
This is how the table entry looks before.
Now continue and examine the address again.
Wh00p.
We changed it.
And that’s the address of hello.
So now continue and let the program run.
BOOM. code execution redirected.
我们赢了！
像printf这样看起来无害的函数如何被用来控制指令真是太疯狂了
指针X