A very common issue that we still constantly encounter is shown in heap level 2 of exploit-exercises.com.
This is a classic use-after-free vulnerability.
Let’s try to understand the code first.
We have here a big while loop inside of main.
在每一轮中，它打印变量auth，该变量是指向此auth对象的指针。
struct up here.
And auth has the attributes name which is a string up to 32 characters and an integer.
另一个被打印的变量是char指针服务，它可以指向
a string in memory.
So both of these are addresses - pointers.
Then we read a line from standard input.
Maximum 128 bytes, so this is a secure fgets read.
No buffer overflow.
然后，我们有几个IFS检查输入行是否是下列之一
commands.
Either “auth”, “reset”, “service” or “login”.
Let’s execute the program as well and then let’s talk about each command.
When we first start the program, both the auth and the service pointer are null.
Now we wait for input.
Let’s have a look at the “auth” command.
当我们键入auth时，它将分配auth结构的大小，因此应该是32字节
for the name + 4 byte for the integer.
Then the whole allocated memory is overwritten with zeroes.
这是有意义的，因为如果在堆中，数据被不断地分配和释放，那么
newly allocated area can have old data in there.
A free does not zero out the memory.
So here it’s zeroes out on allocation.
然后检查输入行的长度，使其不超过32字节
available in the auth struct for the name.
如果这是安全的，那么auth命令后的字符将复制到
the auth object.
Let’s try that, let’s authenticate as admin.
Cool, as we can see the variable auth contains now an address.
This is where the auth object is on the heap.
现在最后一个命令是“login”，它检查auth对象的整数是否为
not zero, and if that’s the case we sucessfully logged in.
Otherwise, if it’s zero, then it tells us to enter a password.
Though in this case there is not more functionality than that.
but just imagine that you are trying to login as admin, without knowing my password.
So somehow our goal is to set the integer to a value, and then we are authenticated.
目前似乎不可能，因为integer auth从未设置在任何位置，但是
we have learned from the beginning, that there are bugs that allow us to modify variables.
Another command here is reset, which will free the auth object on the heap.
And this is actually where the issue is.
您注意到，当我们重置登录过程时，它会释放auth对象，但是正如您所看到的那样
auth变量没有重置为零，它仍然包含指向堆的指针，其中
the object was before.
And when we for example login now, it will check the name attribute of that object.
Well, it hasn’t changed so we are still unauthenticated.
But the login command will “use” the variable auth after we just freed it.
“Use-after-free”.
了解了？
现在这里的最后一个命令是service，它将执行strdup、string duplication，
of the characters after the service command.
So for example we can specify that we want to use the hack service.
And now we also have an address in the service variable.
And strangely it’s the same one as auth.
That is weird.
那么strdup是做什么的呢？
Let’s read the man page.
strdup returns a pointer to a new string which is a dublicate of the string s.
The memory for the new string is obtained with malloc, and can be freed with free.
啊哈。所以它只是一个方便的函数，用来分配字符串的长度
pass to it, and copies it there.
So it will also call malloc and thus allocate stuff on the heap.
你已经可以猜到为什么服务得到和auth相同的地址，因为auth是
freed, there was free space, and service got that free space there.
Let’s look at this in gdb.
First we set the assembler syntax to intel.
And then we disassemble main.
Let’s first run it and use auth once, so we performed at least one malloc.
Then press control+c and check the address of the heap with info proc mappings.
Now we can print 20 words from the heap with examine.
另外，因为这个应用程序仍然拥有二进制文件中的所有符号和内容，
gdb also knows that auth is from the type struct auth, which we can print pretty again.
And we can see here the string name and the auth integer.
We can do the same for the service string.
Now let’s create a breakpoint before the printf.
And with command we can type what (gdb) commands shall be executed when we hit this breakpoint.
We can use echo to print some strings to make it all look more pretty.
First we want to print the heap.
We echo a line.
Then we want to print the auth variable.
Another line.
And the service variable.
At the end we continue automatically.
Finsih the command sequence with end.
Now let’s rerun this binary.
好的，首先我们会得到一些内存错误，因为堆还不存在，所以让我们来看看malloc
our first value by authenticating with “auth” as admin.
另外，让我们禁用gdbs分页，这样我们总是打印所有内容，而不获取
“键入&lt；返回&gt；继续”对话框。关闭分页
Now we can see here our heap.
Like we expect we have here a chunk with our string name admin.
Buuuuut.
Something is weird.
为什么这个块的长度只有十六进制10，即减去
8 byte chunk headers….
它不应该是32字节的名称+整数吗？
怎么了？
好吧，这对解决方案来说并不重要，但如果你写得很糟糕，就会发生这种情况。
code, and name everything auth.
结构称为auth，结构auth指针称为auth，整数位于
here is called auth.
当程序员计算auth的大小时，它计算变量的大小
auth, not the struct auth.
Thus it’s only 4 byte - but malloc aligned it to 8 bytes.
Gosh.
People.
Please name your variables better.
This is how bugs and security issues are created.
Anyhow, let’s ignore that for now.
Earlier we were wondering how the free works.
So let’s free the auth object with reset, and pay attention to what changes.
Ok lol.
Basically nothing changed.
Except that the first word of the chunk data got replaced with 0.
这是因为自由块中的第一个词被定义为前一个自由块
address.
Because free chunks are a linked list.
But we don’t have another free chunk in this list, thus it’s null.
所以除了malloc算法之外，实际上没有发生什么事情
在开始时重新开始，它不关心是否还有剩余值
the heap, as long as the metadata like the previous address pointer are correct.
Thus it only changed that particular value.
不管怎样，我们现在可以看到auth对象仍然存在，指针指向堆中
here.
But the name is now empty with nulls, and the integer is also still null.
But.
Let’s use service to allocate a string on the heap.
Let’s allocate just some recognizable characters.
Like AAA.
Note only 3 As, because the code is shitty and it also takes the space before the As.
Here on the heap we can see that the string got allocated.
And we see that the name of the auth object has now some different values.
Now let’s allocate a new string with service.
BBB.
And another one with CCC.
We see the heap slowly filling up.
哼！
What’s that.
Suddenly the auth integer has a huge value.
That’s because it points into the heap where the CCC is stored.
And if we now login, then we get the message that we are already logged in.
令人惊叹的！
I have to say this level is so horribly broken.
正如我前面提到的，代码太糟糕了，它为auth分配了错误的大小
object.
The space is too small.
I show you.
Let’s restart it and auth again as admin.
Now simply enter a along service string.
And boom, we also overwrite the integer.
And we get the logged in message.
所以我们不需要用reset释放auth对象来解决它，但是我想介绍一下
the term use-after-free and that was also kinda the intended challenge.