让我们从当前Ubuntu上的漏洞攻击练习Protostar中查看格式级别4
machine.
这一次，我想，我们不是从一开始就建立起完整的开发，而是
利用我们为32位Linux映像开发的旧漏洞，看看它是否仍然存在
works.
Probably it won’t but then we debug it and slowly make it work on this 64bit ubuntu.
Okay so here is the source code again.
We have a 512 byte large buffer on the stack, which is used to read data from standard input.
But it only reads up to 512 bytes, so there is no buffer overflow.
But then this buffer is passed directly to printf, so we have a format string exploit.
Our goal is it to redirect code execution to the hello() function.
注意，在printf（）之后，我们如何找到一个出口？
好吧，这是故意放在这里的，因为退出是libc的一部分，所以会有一个全球性的
offset table entry for it which we can overwrite.
Then when we call exit here, our overwritten function would be executed instead.
So it’s actually a pretty straight forward format string exploit.
Just write to the exit GOT entry the address of hello and you are done.
Hello() and the GOT table have fixed addresses and are not affected by ASLR.
At least on this ubuntu version because of the default compiler options.
I received several comments that wrote that on their system they default to PIE.
所以这里的got地址和函数会受到aslr的影响，然后我不
think these simple cases are exploitable anymore.
我们需要一个更复杂的例子，更多的交互，在这里
first can leak values to defeat aslr.
But we will slowly get there, over time.
Let’s not rush too quickly into those topics.
So we compile this now on our ubuntu machine and we get the old exploit code.
伙计，这是第0x13集…
August 2016… holy shit that is a long time ago.
When I started I thought I would have very quickly a complete series on all the basics...
我们还没有到达ROP和ASLR。嗯…
Goddamit.
Anyway.
Let’s copy that python code.
Looks good.
现在我把它写进一个文件--exp，然后我们可以用format4启动gdb并执行
it.
Run and then we pipe in the exp file as input to the program.
Uh we print a lot of character, that looks good but we get a segfault.
We are attempting to write the value in r15, 0x84b4 to the address in rax.
And rax is obviously wrong.
0x58 is X.
So this is the %n part of the exploit.
0x84B4是已经打印的字符数，即这里的所有空格，
and it tried to write to the 4th value, and that turned out to be not the address anymore.
So two things.
首先，显然我们用%n编写的字符数量是错误的，我们
don’t even know yet what we want to write.
And most importantly, we are not writing to the address we have specified in the exploit.
Now with the format string offset we hit our padding.
Okay so let’s use this opportunity and get the correct addresses first.
We need the address of the exit GOT entry, we do this by looking where it is called.
然后我们简单地分解几个跳转到got入口的指令，这就是plt
the procedure linkage table.
And here it references the exit GOT entry.
你可以看到它会跳到写在那里的任何地址，所以我们必须覆盖
this with the address of hello.
And here is the address of hello.
您可以再次看到，只有当前出口的最后2个字节获得了入口和我们想要的
hello address are different.
Which means we only have to overwrite those last two bytes.
所以让我们把这两个新地址放在我们的漏洞代码中，我们也可以扔掉
the old format modifiers.
The amount of characters we print is wrong and the offset doesn’t match anymore either.
And instead we just add a bunch of %p, to find our new stack offset.
So we write it again to a file, start gdb and pipe the file in as input.
嗯…没有实际输出？
就像一个@和一个倒勾？
我们用%p泄露的地址在哪里？
这些小事情真的很让人沮丧
me when I was preparing this episode.
I was going crazy trying to understand what the heck is happening.
I’m just executing it over and over again, hoping the computer would do something else.
I’m debugging it to break before the printf and see that my input is passed to printf.
But no output.
该死的Ghnana工作！
But it will not.
If it’s not doing what i want it to do, I made a mistake.
I am the problem.
我需要冷静下来，退后一步，想办法弄清楚我的蠢货。
mistake.
So what exactly is the output we get.
I pipe the exploit output into hexdump and see that it stops after three characters.
And that is our address but cut off.
The other address and the format string is missing.
But when I then also did the hexdump of the exploit I noticed the obvious mistake.
The address has a null byte.
And printf stops at a null-byte.
Strings are null-terminated.
Godam I’m so dumb.
这不是32位攻击的问题，因为我们的地址也有4个字节
and thus no null-byte.
Now on 64bit the default address is only 3 bytes.
So our next step is - we move the address at the end of our exploit.
They still get placed on the stack with the nullbytes.
fgets will read nullbytes.
Just the printf format vulnerability part must not have a null-byte.
当我们把它移到末尾时，我们希望它在一个固定的位置，所以我们将填充添加到
我们的格式字符串，然后确保在
end.
We are on 64bit, so we have 2 times 8 bytes, so we need 16 characters.
Looks good.
So we try that intput into format4.
Looks good, we print values now.
But I can’t find our address.
Let’s actually have a lot more %p.
How about 100, that fits easily in the 512 bytes.
Ok so where are they.
他们在这儿？
But that doesn’t look good.
They should be two individual values.
But it’s pretty clear what happened.
We forgot to also encode the addresses for 64bit.
Struct pack I packs the integer in 4 bytes, but we want it packed in 8 bytes.
So let’s try it again.
Here they are.
This looks good.
Now let’s find their offset.
We can just count how much to the end.
And then subtract from 100.
So at offset 68 we should find the address.
And yes indeed.
There it is.
So now, we just have to print the correct amount of characters to write the two bytes.
Actually, we don’t need two writes, we should be able to do that in one.
So we add another format string with a padding of the amount of characters we want to write.
That would be 0x676, minus the characters we already printed before that.
So basically minus 8.
然后我们还应该删除%n前面的空格，这将是另一个字符
printed.
所以现在应该可以了，对吧？
让我们将%p更改为%n并尝试它！
Segmentation fault.
该死的…
So when I was recording all of this I really thought it should work right away.
But then I got the segmentation fault.
Really confused me.
And that would be again something I could obsess about.
为什么会这样？
但在我停止录音并开始写下我刚刚做的事情之后，
the script.
I realized my mistake.
当我写下%n
I realized I wrote a whole integer.
But I meant to write only two bytes, so I would have required %hn.
We should be able to verify this with gdb.
Let’s check it out.
Yes there it is.
Segfault at address 0x676.
我们写了一个整数，所以我们重写了已经存储的更高字节。
in the GOT.
So let’s change it to %hn.
To write half a word or whatever that means.
It writes two bytes.
那很管用！代码执行重定向！你赢了
You see the exploit is different from the original 32bit version.
It required quite some changes but it also kinda is still the same thing.
Definitely not a hard challenge on a modern system.
As long as you don’t compile it with PIE.