We have already come a long way in trying
to understand how we can exploit programs
through memory corruption.
We have covered a wide variety of examples,
including basic buffer overflows, format string
exploits and even heap exploits.
And a lot of you might already find it quite
complex.
But if you put it into the context of history
we are still like 16 years behind.
The last examples we have explored from exploit-exercises.com
introduced techniques that were state-of-the-art
in like 2001.
While it still directly applicable to shitty
cheap embedded devices, like some IoT stuff,
it’s very important to lay a foundation.
But before we start talking about all these
modern exploit mitigations and how we can
bypass them, I think it would be a good idea
to try putting what we have learned in more
abstract terms.
And try to get a feeling or an intuition about
exploiting binaries.
Let’s try to create a mental model of exploitation.
But let’s first introduce some constraints,
otherwise it will be too abstract.
Let’s focus on programs like we have interacted
before.
this means intel architecture and on linux.
Ok.
Let’s start at the beginning.
We want programs to execute on our CPU.
That’s why a program contains assembler
code - machine code.
And machine code is just like any other data
in our computers.
It’s basically just bits.
0 and 1s.
A lot of times we combine them into bytes.
And a CPU can interpret a byte as an instruction.
Or multiple bytes can be interpreted as an
instruction.
And some crazy digital hardware magic in the
CPU knows that this particular value stands
for “add the values stored in two registers
and put the result in the first register.
And registers are just like small memory cells
in the CPU, which fullfil different purposes.
And different architectures might have different
registers for different purposes.
But on intel we have for example the general
purpose registers like eax, and ebx, that
a programmer is free to use however he wants
to.
But there are also special registers, like
EIP, the instruction pointer.
That one simply contains the address, which
points to memory, where the next instruction
will be.
And there is also this stack pointer ESP,
which points to the top of the stack, and
the base pointer EBP, which together with
the stack pointer define a stack frame.
And for beginners this might already feel
complicated.
There is code, there is data, there is a stack,
there is a heap.
There are functions you can call.
Functions can return.
Somehow there is like a return pointer on
the stack you can overwrite with a buffer
overflow.
There are a lot of different terms that we
use.
But it’s a lot less complex as it may sound.
Because essentially there are just two parts
that are important
we have memory, which is just a huuuuuuge
space of bits that can be 1 or 0.
Usually we group them in bytes or words.
And there is a CPU, which has a well defined
deterministic behaviour that operates on this
memory.
It’s really that simple.
Well.
The devil is in the practical details, but
essentially, when the CPU is turned on, it
will start at some defined address.
This could be 0, but could also be defined
to be something else.
It request that memory content from some RAM,
looks at the value stored at that address,
and performs the action according to whatever
that value represents.
Now when we want to execute a program, you
can’t just write your code directly into
RAM, and restart the CPU at address 0.
Because if your program would cause an endless
loop, the whole system would stop working.
But when you program an arduino, a little
microcontroller, that’s basically what you
do.
But that’s why some people developed something
like the Linux kernel.
Which abstracts away the direct hardware for
you and makes sure, that if your program sucks,
you don’t kill the whole system.
That’s why a program is not just plain assembler
code, but it’s a fairly complex file format.
An ELF file.
Which does contain your raw code, but also
a lot of other information.
And when you execute this program, the linux
system will actually open the ELF file, read
and interpret all the necessary metadata and
setup the execution environment for you, and
then jumps to the start of your actual code.
So how does the execution environment look
like?
That’s important to picture, because in
that environment, you try to exploit a program,
you need to understand it.
And in some way it’s actyually very simple.
Again, the devil is in the practical details,
but it will make sense.
Let’s say the CPU is just about to execute
your first instruction.
This means the kernel and the hardware magic
has already set up everything.
And this is how it looks like.
You have a big blob of memory.
It ranges from 0, to ffffff.
In reality you don’t really have that much
memory, that’s why we call it virtual memory.
It looks like you own all this memory, but
hardware magic only makes you think you have
it.
But in anyway, the CPU now executes your program
which is somewhere in that huge memory.
Let’s have a look at how this memory is
divided up in a real program.
So for example here, we see that from this
starting address, to this end address, your
program is mapped.
We say mapped, because it’s not really physically
at this address, but it’s there if you would
read the value from that address, in your
assembler code.
So ignore the underlaying physical reality,
and just acccept that there is this huge range
of memory you can work with.
And infact the stack is also just here.
It’s also just defined as starting from
this address and ends at this address.
So the stack is not really growing or shrinking,
that’s just the computer theoretical model
of a stack.
But how is the stack actually defined?
Well the CPU has the stack register, ESP,
and it would contain an address pointing into
this area here.
So could you just point the stack pointer
somewhere else.
Like into your code?
Yeah!
You absolutely could.
The stack pointer is nothing really special,
it’s just a register that contains an address,
and it could contain any address.
What makes ESP actually special is just that
it does some fancy stuff based on instructions.
So for example a pop eax instruction, would
look up what value is stored at the location
where ESP points to, usually that’s the
stack, but doesn’t have to.
And then writes the value from that location
into the eax register.
And you can absolutely abuse that in an exploit.
For example if you find a bug that allows
you to set the stack pointer to a different
value, you could create a fake stack on the
heap, and just point ESP there.
Often times referred to as a stack pivot.
So lose the mental image of a stack that grows
and shrinks that you learned in computer science,
and just think of it what it really is.
It’s just some memory where the ESP register
points to.
And instructions cause interesting effects
based on that register.
And in the same sense the instruction pointer
is not special.
Usually it points into your code, but it doesn’t
have to.
If you manage to control EIP somehow, you
can just point it to other memory.
For example the stack, which we have used
in previous exploits.
Because we placed data that is actually valid
assembler code onto the stack.
You know it as shellcode.
The CPU doesn’t care.
The EIP register points into some memory,
and the CPU just happily does what those values
say.
And well, that is just half true.
Because as you may know, on modern systems
the stack is not executeable anymore, so the
CPU does kinda care, but also not really.
It just means that certain areas in this memory
can have different permissions.
Certain areas have the executable flag which
means the CPU allows EIP to point there and
is happy to interpret the values as instructions,
but other areas like the stack don’t have
it.
And then the CPU refuses to interpret it as
instructions.
Now when we look a bit closer to what kind
of data is included in all those different
memory areas, we can try to come up with creative
ways of how to abuse the.
One example is the typical stack structure.
When the CPU executes a call instruction it
places the current instruction pointer value
at the address where the stack pointer points
to.
It places it ontop of the stack.
And when the function returns it takes the
value where the stack pointer points to and
sets the instruction pointer to it.
So if you somehow manage to modify this value
on the stack, you can control to what EIP
will be set to when the function returns,
and thus you can decide what will be execute
next.
That’s a classical buffer overflow.
Another interesting data structure is the
global offset table, which is basically just
an area in memory containing pointers to functions,
if you overwrite an entry there, you can also
control what will be executed if a function
is called that references an address from
this table.
I mean oftentimes you cannot directly overwrite
these values, but that just means you have
to become creative.
For example think of two objects on the heap.
A user object and a name object, and the user
object has a pointer to the name object.
And when you want to change the name of this
user, the code would follow the pointer and
write the new name to that location, which
means if you can somehow overwrite that pointer,
you can control where it would write the name
to.
So we could overwrite the name pointer with
an address on the stack, and when we write
the new name for the user, we will actually
overwrite the stored instruction pointer on
the stack.
See what I try to get at?
There is memory that contains data.
Some restrictions apply, like certain memory
areas are not writeable, others are not executable.
And there is a CPU that is very dumb and just
executes whatever EIP points to.
And there is a program in the memory, which
the CPU executes.
And this code uses the memory to do whatever
it is supposed to do.
And it trusts in a certain integrity of the
data in memory.
But if there is a bug, that allows you to
change a value in memory, which the program
did not intend to be modifiable, amazing things
could happen.
And what can happen, that’s just limited
by your creativity and imagination.
One changed byte here in memory, might cause
a certain piece of code to write to an unintended
location, which overwrites a function pointer
of an object, which another part of the code
wanted to use, and suddenly executes something
very different.
And all these techniques we assigned names
to, like stack buffer overflow, heap fengshui,
ROP, use-after-free, are all just creative
ways to screw with data in memory and how
the program executed by the CPU reacts to
it.
I understand that this episode might not have
contained actual useful information to you.
But I kinda wanted to get it out there, because
maybe somebody didn’t quite picture programs
and exploits in this way.
But I hope you can see the value in this way
of thinking about it.
I think it takes some away some of the fear
that it all looks so complicated.
I’m really interested to hear your critical
opinion about this.
So comment here on youtube or on the reddit
thread linked below.
But nevermind if you liked this or not, we
will continue soon our path to learn about
more advanced memory corruption techniques.
So, stay curious, and see you next time.