The last few videos were already getting really
difficult to follow and required a lot of
concentration and patience to understand them.
So I’m happy that we can now move on to
the networking challenges from exploit-exercises
protostar, which will be a lot easier because
we have to establish some basics first.
Let’s have quick look at networking level
0.
The description says you have to convert strings
to little endian integers.
And this level is very easy, but to fully
understand what’s going on, the code is
not quite enough.
I show you why.
So main calls a function background_process
and passes it a name and the user and group
ID it will run with.
But this function is not a common libc function.
You can also check /etc/passwd for the user
id 999 and you will notice there is no such
user.
This might seem weird but just don’t think
so abstractly about computers.
What does it mean to have a user on a linux
system?
In the end, a user is just an ID, a number
in memory, and for example an owner of a file
just means that this file has this number
as owner set.
Now if the user is listed here in the /etc/passwd
file, linux will be so nice and display the
name instead of the number, but under the
hood it is still just an integer.
So even though there is no name assigned to
that ID, you are still free to use it.
Anyway, back to the code.
The other functions such as serve_forever
and set_io are also not known functions.
And when you look at the includes, you will
notice that it references a common.c file.
So the author of this challenge implemented
a lot of the code in a different file and
we don’t know what it does.
But one function is here, and that is the
run() function.
You can see that it is called at the end of
main().
Run generated a random number, tells us that
you should send that number as little endian.
Then performs a read from a filedescriptor,
in this case from standard input, interprets
this input as a number and compares if it’s
the same as the random number before.
So just a simple test.
As I said earlier, we could solve the challenge
without knowing these unknown functionsbelow
, because just reading the comments and function
names tells us everything we need to know,
but as you know, we are not satisfied on this
channel when we ignore underlying concepts.
We want to understand computers better.
And these functions implement two interesting
concepts that are mentioned here, one is running
the process as a daemon, and the other one
is about networking and sockets.
So how can we figure out what it does?
Well we know already everything we need, to
be able to reverse engineer this.
So let’s start by exploring the behaviour
of the program before digging deeper.
When you try to run the program, nothing happens.
But when you look at the running processes
you can see that net0 is already running.
So let’s quickly switch to the root user
so we cann kill that process and start it
ourselves.
The default root password for this VM is “godmode”.
Now we can kill net0 and we can verify that
it is not running anymore.
So, let’s execute it again.
Nothing happens?
But if we check the processes we can see that
it’s running again.
So what happened?
Let’s kill it again and start it with strace.
So it finishes with an exit but what happens
before?
It seems to open a net0.pid file with write
permissions.
Then it changes the user and group id to 999
with set effective uid and gid.
So this means the process drops it’s root
permissions, which is uid 1 down to user with
id 999.
After that it calls clone().
The manpages says that clone creates a new
process similar to fork.
So this will spawn a new process as a clone,
a copy, of itself.
And the return value is the process ID of
this new process, which is equal to the value
written into the .pid file.
So that file just helps you keeping track
of the new process you created.
And after that the parent process exits and
leaves the child process orphaned.
This is literally referred to as an orphaned
process and because we did this intentionally
we also refer to this now as a daemon.
It’s now a background process.
So what we can do is, we can run strace with
the -f flag, to follow child processes created
instead of staying in the parent process.
When we do that, we see that after the clone
we attached to the new process and in the
background the old process exits.
Then we change directory and open up /dev/null,
which is another special pseudo file that
acts like a blackhole.
And then we dup the stdinput, stdoutput and
stderror of this process, which basically
means we bend all these standard streams to
point into the blackhole.
Basically we just throw away anything.
And then we write the child’s process id
to the .pid file from earlier which had filedescriptor
number 3.
Now the fun part starts, a new socket is created.
A socket is used for network communications
and you can choose what kind of socket you
want with those flags and settings.
But most importantly is then the call to bind,
which attempts to bind this process here to
the port 2999.
Which means that if the operating system receives
a packet that want’s to establish a connection
with this process, it will do so and then
forward the packet with data inside to the
process.
But!, this function call fails because the
address and port is already in use by another
process.
Which makes sense because we called net0 already
way earlier.
So let’s kill the process again and retry
this.
OKAY!
This looks great.
Now we listen on the port we opened and are
waiting for a packet to arrive with the accept
syscall.
So let’s open a second terminal and use
netstat to find this listening process.
And here it is.
On port 2999 the process net0 is listening.
Cool.
Now let’s use netcat to establish a TCP
connection with this port.
This will cause the accept call to return,
because a new connection got established.
And immediatly after accept you see another
call to clone, which creates another process
to now handle this server-client connection.
This way another user can also establish a
connection and doesn’t have to wait until
you are done, because you have now your own
dedicated process.
Also accept returned a new filedescriptor
that references this socket.
So like with regular files you can now perform
read and write with this filedescriptor, like
you would with any other file.
The kernel underneath makes sure to send the
data you write as a TCP packet to the client.
And when it receives data it will make sure
that you can read it from this socket.
So now it will change the std input, output
and error streams from /dev/null to this new
filedescriptor.
And the program can then just read from stdinput
and will read the data you sent it.
And that is what the run function does.
If you compare run with the last two syscalls
we first have a write to stdout which came
from this printf here, and then an fread from
stdin and this is where we are right now.
When we now type a line into netcat, netcat
will send a packet with this text through
the network to the program, the server.
And on the server side you can see that it
read the string you sent to it, and then it
performed the write telling you that it is
the wrong number.
That’s the failed printf in run().
So let’s summarize what the hidden code
is doing.
It first deamonizes by cloning itself and
killing the parent, to become an orphan.
Then it starts listening on port 2999 for
TCP connections.
Once a connection is established, and we will
have a detailed look at the TCP protocol some
other time, it will create another clone of
the process to handle this established connection.
While the parent is ready again to accept
another connection in parallel.
The child process that handles the connection
is now basically just calling run().
So in simple terms you can say, the program
runs as a background process that executes
run() for every client that connects to it.
Awesome!
We understood that.
Now let’s solve the challenge.
First of all we need to get the string representation
of that number.
We can use python for that, specifically the
struct package - which we already used before.
So with struct.pack we can convert a number
to the byte string representation.
But as you can see, the resulting string doesn’t
use characters we can type with the keyboard.
We can print these byte values with echo and
-e, but simply piping this into nc doesn’t
work, because the number is randomized.
But we can use a simple trick.
We can use echo -e, but inside of the quotes
we use backticks to execute cat with a minus,
which simply redirects anything we type to
the output again, and the output is then placed
in the quotes of echo.
So when we now pipe that into netcat, we see
the number and cat is waiting for input, we
use python to convert the number and then
we simply paste the escape string back into
the other terminal, hit enter and then use
CTRL+D, to indicate we are done with input,
which closes cat and echo will send the string
to netcat.
And that works, we get the sucess “thank
you sir/madam message”.