So we finished exploit-exercises protostar
a while ago.
Which means we have a really good basic understanding
of how binary exploitation worked, many years
ago.
Exploitation nowadays is not as easy anymore
and some of you have noticed that, because
you tried to copy the source code and compile
it on their own modern linux machine.
So I thought it would be interesting to start
introducing modern techniques and exploit
mitigations by revisiting some of the protostar
challenges on a current ubuntu.
And see how far we get.
Are they still exploitable?
So let’s have a quick look at the very simple
source code again.
There were these variables, a buffer and this
modified integer which was set to 0.
Then there was this gets() function which
reads in some input into the buffer and it
doesn’t have a way to check the length.
So this way we were able to fill the buffer
completely and even write beyond it, into
adjacent memory.
The binary on the old protostar VM had the
modified variable just after the buffer.
Thus if you wrote more than 64 bytes you overwrote
the 0 value of the modified variable and thus
change the outcome of this if.
So let’s try this again on a modern system.
I’m using digitalocean to quickly spin up
a new ubuntu linux machine and ssh into it.
Then I take the code and compile it.
Oh, new system.
So we also have to install gcc, the compiler.
Now it works.
You can already see that the compiler is warning
us of the use of gets().
You see, making programming mistakes like
this really requires a developer to ignore
warnings like this.
You don’t really have to know about the
dangers from somewhere else anymore, it tells
you right away.
So let’s see.
Let’s try to input a lot of characters and
see if we can change the modified variable.
But it doesn’t seem to work.
The only thing we can get is a stack smashing
detected error.
And the process is aborted.
That’s the first evidence that a bit more
stuff is going on here.
So let’s look at the assembly code that
the compiler produced.
First of all let’s check why we couldn’t
overwrite the modified variable.
Does the stack smashing detected have to do
anything with it?
Mh kinda.
But let’s see.
You see this location on the stack is where
the local variable modified is stored.
You can see that because the value 0 is moved
to it, like in the C code.
And this here is the buffer on the stack you
can see that because the address of it is
passed to gets.
Like in the C code.
So when you look at this you notice, that
the modified variable is NOT located after
the buffer anymore.
We can write as many characters as we want,
but we will never overwrite modified.
You can also try to reorder the variables
in the C code but that has no effect on the
assembler code either.
And that’s not a coincidence.
Buffers or arrays are risky compared to simple
integer variables.
Buffers are prone to buffer overflows.
So the compiler made the decision to order
the local variables in a particular way.
And it kinda has something to do with the
stack smashing detected message.
You see this message is caused because a stack
cookie or stack canary or stack guard was
overwritten.
So what exactly is that?
Let’s open the compiled binary in a disassembler
to have a better look at it.
If you are still learning about this stuff,
assembler code always looks very intimidating.
But it’s all about recognizing and learning
patterns.
One such pattern is here with the stack cookies.
Because when you reverse engineer a program,
you can basically ignore a lot of stuff.
For example this here and down here, has to
do with the stack cookie, and so it has nothing
to do with the functionality of the program.
If you are interested in what this function
roughly does, you can look for functions being
called here, so there is a gets, so that is
reading something.
Then a local variable is compared and then
it prints a string with puts in either case.
So you already get a rough idea from that.
But we already know what it does, so whats
up with the parts of the stack cookie.
In the beginning of the function a value was
moved from a weird place, fs at offset hex
28, into the register rax.
And then that value is placed onto the stack.
And at the end of the function, just before
the return, this value is read again from
the stack and then xored with this mysterious
value in fs hex 28.
This is just a check if the two values are
the same.
If they are equal the function is allowed
to return.
If the check failed, and those values are
different, then there is a call to stack_check_fail
and the program will never return.
And this makes sense right.
So some unknown value is written onto the
stack at the beginning, then stuff happens,
for example the gets() call which can overflow
the buffer,
And at the end the value on the stack is compared
again to this mysterious value.
So if we had a buffer overflow that overwrote
this stack cookie, this check would fail.
So fs, or gs or other segment registers, are
special registers with varying usages depending
on 32bit or 64bit and if you are on windows
or linux and if you write low level boot or
kernel ring 0 code or if you write userspace
ring 3 programs.
And there is a lot of historical baggage with
them.
And to be completely honest with you, I don’t
fully understand it.
Maybe somebody in the comments can correct
me and add some additional information.
So take this explanation with a grain of salt.
You can imagine the fs register to point to
some memory.
And from the perspective of the process we
actually don’t really know where it points
to.
The kernel (I think) set up where it points
So the process doesn’t really care where
it points to, it can just use it.
And it can then reference different values
at certain offsets in that memory.
So for example the stack cookie is stored
at offset hex 28.
And actually the location must be somewhere
in the virtual memory of the process as well.
Let’s install the gdb enhancment peda really
quick because it has a great memory find function.
we can test this by setting a breakpoint at
the stack cookie handling routines and search
the process memory for this value.
And you can see it shows up in some kind of
mapped memory.
And if you check the memory maps it is included
here.
And that is really the location where fs points
to.
Because for example we can now overwrite this
value with hex 41, so capital AAAAAAA.
And when we continue and enter a lot of data,
a lot of As we will overwrite the cookie on
the stack with hex 414141.
And when we now reach the end of the function
the stack cookie value was obviously overwritten
by us with 414141.
But we also just set by hand the original
value of the stack cookie to 41414.
And even though we cannot inspect and see
where fs points to, the CPU knows where the
value is and will compare those two now.
And not suprisingly we continue to the return
and get a segfault.
Instead of going to the stack_check_fail.
This means we actually have changed the original
value of the stack cookie.
That’s cool huh?
But you see it’s not really a bypass for
cookies, it doesn’t help us in this particular
case and magically make it exploitable.
We are just playing around with it to understand
it better.
And we know that the original stack cookie
value is stored somewhere in memory.
So those cookies serve a precise purpose,
but it’s not the magic medicine that stops
every exploit attempt.
But now you have a better understand of the
limitations of stack cookies, they are just
a value on the stack which are placed there
at the beginning of a function and compared
to the original value before the function
returns.
This means we can overwrite the return pointer
on the stack, but the issue is, that the function
will never return because the cookie is wrong.
And if there are other variables on the stack
before the cookie they could all be still
overwritten.
So it actually just kinda protects you from
smashing the return pointer for a classic
buffer overflow.
It only stops the function form returning,
but it might not stop other side effects due
to things overwritten on the stack.
So in our case, theoretically if the modified
variable would have been placed after the
buffer, we could have still overwritten it
without ever writing so far that we overwrite
the stack cookie.
But the compiler developers know that buffer
overflows are a common thing, so they want
buffers to be as close as possible to the
stack cookie.
Which causes the modified and buffer variable
to be reordered in this way.
The buffer is placed after the modified variable,
closer to the cookie.
Darn it.
There is another interesting thing about stack
cookies.
Let’s rerun the program and collect a few
random cookies.
Do you notice something, they all start with
a zero byte.
So this is the little endian format but in
memory the bytes would look like this.
So that’s interesting.
Why would they not use all 8 bytes for random
values but compromise one of these bytes to
be a static 0.
Doesn’t that make it weaker, because now
you only have to bruteforce, eh guess, 7 bytes?
There are obviously various ways how you can
attack a stack cookie, it obviously should
not be guessable or bruteforcable, but 7 bytes
is huuuuge number already.
So probably good enough.
But as you know there are a lot of ways to
leak values from memory for example with format
string exploits.
So you use that to leak a stack cookie value
and then your overflow is trivial again.
But some overflows happen because of a strcpy.
And strings in C are zero terminated.
So even if you would know the stack cookie,
and you have a vulnerable strcpy, you can
never overwrite the cookie with the corerct
value, because you cannot write a 0 byte.
Because a null byte marks the end of a string
in c.
But in our example uses gets() and according
to the man page you can see that gets actually
only stops at a newline, so you could write
0 bytes with that.
So it’s a very clever choice to include
a 0 byte in the cookie.
It’s an additional protection against strcpys,
even if the cookie value is known.
But maybe you ask yourself now, what about
32bit?
Is there also a byte used for a null byte?
Let’s find out.
To compile a 32bit program on 64bit you have
to install some other stuff.
And we can also quickly check if this is not
exploitable.
And you can see that we also only get the
stack smash protection error.
Ok.
So let’s extract some stack cookies here.
You can also see that a different segment
register is used here on 32bit.
But same concept.
And who would have thought.
Also a 0 byte in it.
So this makes only 3 bytes of randomness.
16 million possible values.
&lt;painful noise&gt; mhmh
That sounds a bit more scary.
16 million depending on the context where
and how the program is run is not much.
Maybe in our case it might actually make it
exploitable.
I mean the original protostar VM was also
32bit, so I think it’s fair game.
But to be fair, 64bit probably makes it unexploitable.
So the plan is clear.
We write a program that calls this 32bit version
of stack level 0 all the time and send an
exploit string to it, which uses random cookie
cookie values to bruteforce it.
And at some point we might get lucky, guessed
the correct cookie value, overflow the return
pointer and redirect code execution to the
output, the if case, we want.
Well.
The plan sounds good.
If it were just this easy.
We will need a bit more time for this so let’s
do it in another video.
But it’s a fun challenge, so you should
try that too.