We can use static analysis and reverse engineer
the license check algorithm and write a keygen
to generate valid keys. Obviously this algorithm
also can become very complex but generally,
if you put a lot of work in it, you can figure
it out.
Now you tell that to your manager, but he
is a smart ass and tells you: “then stop
people from being able to reverse engineer
the binary”. Then you drag yourself back
to the desk and you come up with a new creative
way how to stop somebody from debugging or
reversing it.
Because you are a pro, you understand that
a executable is a very complicated file format.
With objdump we have seen that this executable
has a lot of information in there, that is
needed to load and execute it. But you also
realise that a program like gdb has to parse
the executable to be able to disassemble and
debug it. And radare has to read and parse
the executable file to show you stuff. So
could you modify the executable in a way,
that you can still execute it with linux,
but gdb and radare tell you that something
is broken?
What we are looking for is a parser differential.
We hope that the parser from execve differs
from the gdb parser. In an ideal world, every
program that reads input, would do it in the
exact same way. But every tool implements
the parsing algorithm a bit different. So
if you screw with the input, a linux might
see a valid file and executes it, while a
gdb says its broken and cannot be disassembled.
Let me show you a very naive way how to find
something like that. With fuzzing.
So lets create a new python script called
fuzz_elf.py.
First we import some modules we need. Import
random. And import os.
First function we will write is called flip_byte.
As a parameter it takes a big string. Which
will be the whole executable file later. Then
we select a random index i, between 0 and
the max length of the input. Then we select
a random character that we will use to overwrite
a byte in the program. So character byte from
a random number between 0 and FF, which is
255. Then we return the original bytes up
to index i. The next character will be the
random created one, instead of the original
character i at this point. And we append the
remaining original bytes. If you want to understand
this fancy bracket colon index stuff in python,
just google ‘python lists’.
So just a quick example of this function.
print flip_bytes(“ASD123”)
With yy you can copy this line and with p
you can paste it multiple times.
And now you can see that a random character
got changed to something else.
With dd you can delete those lines again.
Now we want a function that copies the original
binary but flips a byte and saves it in another
file. We call this function copy binary. So
we open the normal license_2 and a copy license_2_fuzz
with write access.
Now we read the whole original file, and pass
those bytes to the flip_byte function. Now
this returns a copy of our license_2 executable,
just with a random byte flipped. And then
we write this to the copy.
If we just run this now, the new license_2_fuzz
file will be not executable, so I already
create this file as a copy from the original,
and it will be executable.
Now obviously we flip weird stuff. And the
file might not be executable anymore. So we
should check if the program still works the
same way. This means, that it should print
Access Granted with a valid key. So this output
should be the same for the original and the
fuzz program. That’s why I redirect this
output to a file called, original_output.
Now let’s write a python function that runs
the fuzz binary once a byte got flipped and
let’s check if it outputs the same thing.
A really ugly way how I do this now, just
because it’s less code, I execute the same
command like I just did, just pipe the output
into fuzz_output.
Now I add a function to compare the original
output with the fuzz output. And also let
that result return from the check output function.
Ok so this function checks if the binary still
executes normally.
Now let’s think about how we can check if
gdb still works. Basically we don’t want
people to disassemble main. So you can use
echo and pipe this command and quit into gdb
to get the output. So echo -e and this here
just basically types those two commands and
with the pipe we redirect this to the input
of gdb. This looks good. so let’s simply
redirect this output also to a file, that
I will call original_gdb.
Now let’s basically create the same function,
just with check gdb.
And then compare those two files. Now let’s
to the same for radare2. Here we just use
the commands aaa, s sym.main and pdf. Also
store this output in a file. And now again
we create a check radare function.
You can use Shift V, which you can use to
highlight multiple lines, and with y you can
copy it and paste it with p.
Ok… almost there. Now let’s create an
endless loop. Where we first create a new
copy. Then we check if the executable still
works. If that works we want radare and gdb
to fail. So let’s do if not check_gdb and
not check_radare. If we reach this here, we
print success and exit.
Then we print the tail of the radare and gdb
output. Just to have a visual check if the
disassembly failed in a way. With raw_input
we can halt the python program until we hit
enter.
Now let’s run it. Ah another small mistake.
this should be f1 instead of fn1.
And I just discovered another mistake.
Ok it found something, but we clearly still
se disassembly there. So let’s just continue
until we find an output without disassembly.
Uh. that looks good. Let’s investigate.
Binary still works.
Gdb can’t find a main function.
And radare also has problems.
Haha! that is cool :D
I admit, this is very ugly. This is not really
a good technique that you can use in practice.
But that is basically how fuzzing works. And
how you might discover cool new tricks to
hide your malware and make it harder for people
to analyse it.
If you want to learn more about this you can
read this one, which calls this a “novel
technique”, but it is not really new. And
there is a bit more in depth research on the
ELF file format from IOActive.
And you can go even deeper and read even more
crazy ELF file format tricks in the holy “International
Journal of PoC || GTFO - Issue 0x00“
My binary can be found in the github repository
and you can try different tools like hopper
or IDA and see if they still analyse it automatically.
But I suspect they do. So this is just one
small trick which can annoy somebody trying
to analyse it.
Now you can go back to your manager and tell
him, that he should hire some web developers
and move the product into the cloud, so that
the code only runs on the servers you control.