This is the 10th episode.
And as you can see in the title, I am counting
the episodes in hexadecimal.
I am wondering if the google algorithm will
screw this up with the suggested next video
is wrong.
Anyway, I want to explain in this video why
hexadecimal is cool and why you should use
it, when it comes to computers.
I will also show you how I convert values
back and forth and how I often work with them.
Ok.
So.
our computers work in binary, 0s and 1s.
Because it is a representation of the physical
behaviour of our circuits that we have transistors,
that are like switches and they are either
turned on or off.
A single value that is either 0 or 1 is called
a bit.
You may know that a byte is 8 bits.
But maybe you wonder why that is.
Well, this was not always the case.
Early computers might have had 6 bits per
byte.
That we use 8 bits for a byte nowadays is
just how history turned out.
It was IBMs fault with the System 360 that
heavily pushed for an 8-bit byte.
Also some people say octad instead of byte
to make clear that they mean 8 bit.
An interesting example is ascii, because you
will notice that it actually only uses 7bit.
But because we now generally use 8bit bytes,
we kind of waste the first bit.
We humans grew up with the decimal system.
We are used to counting with symbols from
0 to 9.
But that is rather arbitrary.
Sure, we have 10 fingers.
But we could also count in 12ths, because
we have 12 finger bones and we can use the
thumb to point to which number we are at.
This is the Duodecimal system and we actually
use it on our clock.
So If you would have grown up with counting
in hex or binary, it would feel as natural
to you.
Instead of thinking of numbers as something
fixed, think of it as a tool.
And you can use whichever number system makes
sense for a particular problem.
So our computers work with bits.
And for our modern computers we have defined
that we generally work with bytes of 8 bits.
And 16bit, 32bit or 64bit architectures just
play with this value to keep it nicely divisible
by 8.
When we look at data as raw bits: 0000 0000,
we quickly see that a byte takes a lot of
space if we display it in that way.
Maybe decimal would be a cool representation.
It certainly would take less space to display
them.
I will use python now to show you how we can
convert binary to decimal numbers.
We simply say that this string represents
a number in base 2.
Let’s do it for a couple of examples with
a simple for loop.
Ok.
Well.
Takes less space.
Though, it kinda bothers me that the biggest
value with 8 bits, is a weird number in decimal.
A number without any interesting properties
or meanings.
Let’s have a look at those numbers in hex.
Hex numbers use symbols from 0-9 and A-F to
describe a number.
We can extend our loop in python.
And now you can see how pretty hexadecimal
numbers are to represent 8 bits.
The biggest 8 bit value is also the biggest
value in hex that can be represented by two
digits.
If we would add 1 more bit, so that we have
9 bits, we would also have to add another
character.
And not only that, if you look closely, it
also nicely represents the two individual
nibbles, that means 4 bits.
So a 8 bit number in hex can be represented
by 2 symbols.
And each symbol refers to one nibble.
So this makes it very very clear and easy
to read.
And now you can understand why the decimal
representation is not very fitting for this
kind of stuff.
Can you tell me what is the maximum number
that an unsigned 32bit integer can represent?
Well I don’t know in decimal.
I just know that 32bit is 4 times 8 bit and
thus max int is 0xFFFFFFFF.
Now let me quickly show you some cool tricks
with python to convert stuff back and forth.
Python has some builtin functions to convert
numbers.
For example hex() and bin().
And also to parse a binary or hex number with
the int() function and specifying which base
it is.
If you have a binary string, this means that
maybe not every value in this string is a
nice ascii printable character, you can use
encode and decode on the string to get the
hex representation of the characters.
So hex 41 is a capital ‘A’ in ascii.
A much more powerful and important functionality
is offered by python structs.
Which I use all the time when I deal with
binary data.
First import struct.
And then we can use struct.unpack on our data.
In this case I define that this data is an
unsigned Integer.
And you can see I can convert this binary
data now to an integer number.
If you look closely you may wonder why the
capital A seems to be at the end of the number.
The reason for that is that we have a little-endian
system.
bit’s can be interpreted in two ways.
Either the first or the last bit can refer
to the least-significant bit.
I think the picture on wikipedia makes this
very clear.
This can be very important when you receive
data from a big-endian system, because then
you have to be careful how you interpret this
data.
But with python struct it’s easy and we
can define as which endian system we want
to interpret this data.
If you watch some of my CTF exploitation challenge
videos, you will see me using python structs
a lot.
Because it’s great to convert addresses
and other data back and forth.
For example if we want to overwrite an address,
we have to supply the data as a string.
So we can use struct.pack and pack a number
as a binary string.
So the hexadecimal system makes working with
computers much more simple and you should
get used to it.
But we just talked about positive numbers.
From 0 to 0xFF.
But how can we represent negative numbers.
Maybe you have heard of the signed bit, that
the first bit tells you if it is a negative
number or not.
Though, it’s not as simple as simply reading
the remaining 7 bit and decide if it’s positive
or negative based on the first one.
-1 is actually 0xFF.
Well it does have the first bit set, but it’s
not -127.
This wheel maybe makes it a bit more clear
how negative numbers are actually interpreted.
The operation to convert their absolute value
into the negative value, so for example 255
(0xFF) to -1 is called Two’s complement,
you can read that on wikipedia.
And you can also very easily negate a given
number by negating all bits and adding 1.
Many functions return -1 on error.
At first it sounds weird, but now you know
that this is just all Fs.
So when you read data and you only get 1s
(or Fs in hex) you might read an errror.
What about numbers with a fraction.
Well.
Don’t get me started on that.
It get’s really ugly.
But you can guess that representing a value
with many digits behind the comma can get
very creative if you have only 0s and 1s.
Now before we end let’s get a summary of
the terminology:
we start with a bit.
0 or 1.
4 bits are a nibble.
8 bits are a byte.
And in hexadecimal we can represent a byte
with two digits.
on 32bit architecture a word refers to 32bit
or 4 bytes.
But on 64bit architecture a word is 64bit,
or 8 bytes.
And a double word is obviously the double
amount of that.
As you can see, a computer only has bits.
And how we deal with those bits is up to our
interpretation.
I know this was a bit shorter and less technical
video, but I thought it fits and next time
we will dive deep and exploit our first buffer
overflow.