A very common issue that we still constantly
encounter is shown in heap level 2 of exploit-exercises.com.
This is a classic use-after-free vulnerability.
Let’s try to understand the code first.
We have here a big while loop inside of main.
In each round it prints the variable auth,
which is a pointer to an object of this auth
struct up here.
And auth has the attributes name which is
a string up to 32 characters and an integer.
And the other variable that is printed is
a char pointer service, which can point to
a string in memory.
So both of these are addresses - pointers.
Then we read a line from standard input.
Maximum 128 bytes, so this is a secure fgets
read.
No buffer overflow.
Afterwards we have a couple of ifs that check
if the input line is one of the following
commands.
Either “auth”, “reset”, “service”
or “login”.
Let’s execute the program as well and then
let’s talk about each command.
When we first start the program, both the
auth and the service pointer are null.
Now we wait for input.
Let’s have a look at the “auth” command.
When we type auth, it will allocate the size
of the auth struct, so that should be 32byte
for the name + 4 byte for the integer.
Then the whole allocated memory is overwritten
with zeroes.
This makes sense because if on the heap, data
is constantly allocated and freed, then a
newly allocated area can have old data in
there.
A free does not zero out the memory.
So here it’s zeroes out on allocation.
Afterwards the length of the input line is
checked, so it doesn’t exceed the 32 bytes
available in the auth struct for the name.
And if that is safe, the characters after
the auth command are copied to the name of
the auth object.
Let’s try that, let’s authenticate as
admin.
Cool, as we can see the variable auth contains
now an address.
This is where the auth object is on the heap.
Now the last command is “login”, which
checks if the integer of the auth object is
not zero, and if that’s the case we sucessfully
logged in.
Otherwise, if it’s zero, then it tells us
to enter a password.
Though in this case there is not more functionality
than that.
but just imagine that you are trying to login
as admin, without knowing my password.
So somehow our goal is to set the integer
to a value, and then we are authenticated.
At the moment it seems impossible, because
the integer auth is never set anywhere, but
we have learned from the beginning, that there
are bugs that allow us to modify variables.
Another command here is reset, which will
free the auth object on the heap.
And this is actually where the issue is.
You notice when we reset the login process,
it frees the auth object, but as you can see
the auth variable is not reset to zero, it
still contains the pointer into the heap where
the object was before.
And when we for example login now, it will
check the name attribute of that object.
Well, it hasn’t changed so we are still
unauthenticated.
But the login command will “use” the variable
auth after we just freed it.
“Use-after-free”.
Get it?
Now the last command here is service, which
will perform a strdup, a string dublication,
of the characters after the service command.
So for example we can specify that we want
to use the hack service.
And now we also have an address in the service
variable.
And strangely it’s the same one as auth.
That is weird.
So what does strdup do?
Let’s read the man page.
strdup returns a pointer to a new string which
is a dublicate of the string s.
The memory for the new string is obtained
with malloc, and can be freed with free.
Ahhh. so it’s just a convinient function
that allocates the length of the string we
pass to it, and copies it there.
So it will also call malloc and thus allocate
stuff on the heap.
And you can already guess why service got
the same address as auth, because auth was
freed, there was free space, and service got
that free space there.
Let’s look at this in gdb.
First we set the assembler syntax to intel.
And then we disassemble main.
Let’s first run it and use auth once, so
we performed at least one malloc.
Then press control+c and check the address
of the heap with info proc mappings.
Now we can print 20 words from the heap with
examine.
Also because this application has still all
the symbols and stuff inside of the binary,
gdb also knows that auth is from the type
struct auth, which we can print pretty again.
And we can see here the string name and the
auth integer.
We can do the same for the service string.
Now let’s create a breakpoint before the
printf.
And with command we can type what (gdb) commands
shall be executed when we hit this breakpoint.
We can use echo to print some strings to make
it all look more pretty.
First we want to print the heap.
We echo a line.
Then we want to print the auth variable.
Another line.
And the service variable.
At the end we continue automatically.
Finsih the command sequence with end.
Now let’s rerun this binary.
Ok at first we get some memory errors because
the heap doesn’t exist yet, so let’s malloc
our first value by authenticating with “auth”
as admin.
Also let’s disable gdbs pagination so we
always print everything and don’t get the
“type &lt;return&gt; to continue” dialog.
set pagination off
Now we can see here our heap.
Like we expect we have here a chunk with our
string name admin.
Buuuuut.
Something is weird.
Why is the length of this chunk only hex 10,
that is only 8 bytes after you subtract the
8 byte chunk headers….
Shouldn’t it be 32byt name + the integer?
What’s going on?
Well this is not that important for the solution,
but this is what happens if you write shitty
code, and name everything auth.
The struct is called auth, the struct auth
pointer is called auth and the integer in
here is called auth.
And when the programmer calculated the size
of auth, it calculated the size of the variable
auth, not the struct auth.
Thus it’s only 4 byte - but malloc aligned
it to 8 bytes.
Gosh.
People.
Please name your variables better.
This is how bugs and security issues are created.
Anyhow, let’s ignore that for now.
Earlier we were wondering how the free works.
So let’s free the auth object with reset,
and pay attention to what changes.
Ok lol.
Basically nothing changed.
Except that the first word of the chunk data
got replaced with 0.
That’s because this first word in a free
chunk is defined as the previous free chunk
address.
Because free chunks are a linked list.
But we don’t have another free chunk in
this list, thus it’s null.
So really not much happened, other than the
malloc algorithm knows that the free heap
starts again at the beginning and it doesn’t
care if there are still leftover values on
the heap, as long as the metadata like the
previous address pointer are correct.
Thus it only changed that particular value.
Anyhow, we can now see that the auth object
still exists with the pointer into the heap
here.
But the name is now empty with nulls, and
the integer is also still null.
But.
Let’s use service to allocate a string on
the heap.
Let’s allocate just some recognizable characters.
Like AAA.
Note only 3 As, because the code is shitty
and it also takes the space before the As.
Here on the heap we can see that the string
got allocated.
And we see that the name of the auth object
has now some different values.
Now let’s allocate a new string with service.
BBB.
And another one with CCC.
We see the heap slowly filling up.
And huh!
What’s that.
Suddenly the auth integer has a huge value.
That’s because it points into the heap where
the CCC is stored.
And if we now login, then we get the message
that we are already logged in.
Awesome!
I have to say this level is so horribly broken.
As I mentioned before the code is so shitty
that it allocates the wrong size for the auth
object.
The space is too small.
I show you.
Let’s restart it and auth again as admin.
Now simply enter a along service string.
And boom, we also overwrite the integer.
And we get the logged in message.
So we didn’t have to free the auth object
with reset to solve it, but I wanted to introduce
the term use-after-free and that was also
kinda the intended challenge.