Okay,
So last video I showed you this programming
language I made, ugly but works.
And we compiled this into this weird binary
format.
And then you pass this binary file to this
program called invoice, and it executes our
program.
In the last video I also showed you, that
the beginning of this binary format actually
triggers a buffer overflow and overwrites
the return pointer on the stack.
And at that point you might have thought that
our programs are simply shellcode, so assembler
code, that we inject and then jump to, with
the buffer overflow.
But that is not even possible, because the
stack is not executable.
So even though we cannot inject actual assembler
instructions to execute, we somehow were still
able to execute my programs.
And at this point it’s pretty clear, that
this is possible thanks to return-oriented-programming.
So let’s examine how this works.
But I warn you.
You really need to get your brain into an
abstract philosophical thinking mode.
This will get weird.
And maybe you have to rewatch it some time
in the future, maybe checkout some more “normal”
Return Oriented Programming tutorials and
then come back to this.
But if you get this video, I think it will
add to a much greater and deeper understanding
for you.
So just try...
Anyway.
Let’s head in.
So in x86 assembler there is an instuction
called “call”.
And call actually does two things.
First it pushes the return address (which
is the address immediately after the CALL
instruction) on the stack.
And then it changes EIP, the current instruction
pointer, to the call destination.
So the CPU continues execution there.
Now when we in C call a function, this will
be compiled to an assembler call instruction.
But to understand return-oriented-programming,
you have to forget this.
Ignore the concept of calling functions.
Simply remember that this instruction pushes
the address immediately after the call instruction
onto the stack, and then set instruction pointer
to the target address.
And the return instruction behaves in the
same way.
YES ret is compiled from a return in C. But
forget this connection.
A RET simply pops an address, we call it the
return address, off the stack and sets the
instruction pointer back to that.
And “pooping a value” from the stack is
also already again an abstract interpretation.
What it literally means is, it looks at the
stack pointer register, follows that address,
takes that value.
And then it increments the stack pointer register.
It increments because the stack grows downwards.
So if we shrink it, when we POP a value, we
increase it.
So it gets closer to the highest address again.
Anyway.
This is what ret does.
It’s taking this value where the stack register
points to, increments the stack pointer address,
and then uses the value it got, to set the
instruction pointer.That’s how we “return”
(in quotation marks).
So this was lesson one.
Ignore the name of the instruction or it’s
typical meaning and typical usage, just understand
what the instruction itself does.
So again, remember what the “ret” (the
return) instruction does.
First look at the stack register, follow this
address and take that value.
Increment the stack pointer.
Set the instruction pointer to that value.
Done.
Now let’s think about something else.
What does it mean for a machine to execute
instructions?
A CPU is a piece of hardware that executes
instructions.
Those instructions are machine code or assembler
code, right?
How does that in an abstract sense work?
Well there is memory, where instructions are
stored, and this memory has addresses.
Then the CPU has an instruction pointer register,
that contains an address that points to memory
with the next instruction to execute.
So if it’s 0, it will execute this.
And then it does whatever this instruction
is defined to do.
Not that important what this instruction exactly
does.
But by executing any instruction, the instruction
pointer is simply incremented and moved forward
to point to the next instruction.
ANd then that gets executed and the instruction
pointer will be updated to point to the next
one.
And so forth.
Of course that changes with instructions like
jumps, or calls, or returns, where the instruction
pointer is directly updated.
But you get it.
A computer, really in the abstract sense,
is a machine that given instructions computes
or executes those instructions.
So the CPU is a machine implemented in hardware.
But of course there are also virtual machines.
So machines implemented on top of our CPU
machines.
And for example the JVM, the Java Virtual
Machine behaves in the same way.
It is a machine.
So there is bytecode somewhere in memory,
and the software, the JVM has an instruction
pointer, or there called programm counter
pc, that points to the next instuction, or
there called opcode.
And when the JVM executes one opcode it also
has to update the program counter and move
it to the next one.
Here I looked up the source code for that.
So here is the OpenJDK source code
And there you see an UPDATE_PC_AND_CONTINUE
macro, where it literally adds the size (or
length) of the current opcode onto the program
counter, so this moves it forward.
Like the CPU would increment the instruction
pointer.
So this is lesson two.
A machine in an abstract sense is simple.
There is memory that holds code or instructions.
And the machine points to that code, takes
an instruction, executes it, and then updates
the program counter to point to the next one.
So what the f’ does this have to do with
return oriented programming?
Well last video I also introduced the concept
of a weird machine.
Somehow this invoice program implemented a
weird machine.
And I know, that concept was super confusing
but bear with me, it will make sense in a
moment.
If this invoice program implements a weird
machine, and you program that weird machine
with a technique called return-oriented-programming,
then you should ask yourself now.
where is the memory that contains our instructions,
where is the instruction pointer that points
to those instructions, and where is the logic
that executes whatever an instruction is defined
to do?
Well, luckily we have some example programs,
and we can debug this weird machine with GDB.
Let’s load the invoice program into GDB
and let’s learn how it executes.
I don’t want to explain buffer overflows
again, please checkout my binary exploitation
playlist for that.
But when you are familiar with it, you know
that we overwrote stuff on the stack.
If you look at the add_invoice function you
can find the dangerous functions gets() which
cause the buffer overflow.
So we can set a breakpoint here, and we set
one at the return.
Then let’s run the binary and as an input
we pass in the helloworld.binary.
And we know now that input triggers the buffer
overflow.
So here we hit the breakpoint at the gets.
If we execute the gets and examine th stack,
we can find all of our input here.
Here are all the As that fill up the buffer.
And then we have these randomly looking, but
actually carefully chosen values after it.
But let’s go forward to the return instruction.
So now we are about to execute the return,
and please remember what return means.
It looks at the address in the stack register,
so here this address points to this memory,
so this is the stack and that’s the top
element.
And the return instruction now takes that
value as an address, and sets the instruction
pointer to it.
And at the same time increments the stack
pointer.
So let’s do that.
Single step forward.
ANd now let’s compare before and after the
return.
It did exactly what we expected.
The stack pointer register was incremented
from 0x18 to 0x20, so move 8 bytes forward.
And the instruction pointer got set to the
value previously on top of the stack.
Btw... when we execute a “ret” we also
often use the phrase “we return into &lt;something&gt;”.
It doesn’t matter if we say “we returned
to”, say “we returned into” or say “we
continued execution here”.
It’s all the same.
Don’t get confused by the term “return”.
You know what the ret instruction really does.
It simply takes a value from the stack and
sets the instruction pointer to it.
Anyway.
So what happens now?
Where is our instruction pointer pointing
to?
It points here...
To this assembler code.
A pop rdx and a pop rbx.
Followed by another return?
So this means it takes one value from the
stack and puts it into rdx.
Increments rsp again.
Then takes the next value on the stack and
moves it into rbx.
Increments rsp and then we are at the return
again.
And now return takes the next value on the
stack and sets the instruction pointer to
it.
So where does it now continue executing?
Okay.
So now we are here?
Here we have a pop rdi.
So it takes the next value on the stack, moves
it into rdi.
And then comes ret, which takes the next value
and sets the instruction pointer to it.
So where are we now?
Now we execute a move.
We move edx, into the address pointed to by
rdi.
And remember when we set EDX?
The pop RDX at the beginning, set the value
of EDX to a value we had on the stack.
And RDI, the address where we now write to,
we also had on the stack and got it into RDI
with a pop RDI.
Think about what this code now did!
I know it looked weird, but all it did was
it moved a value we wanted into an address
we specified.
We moved a value into RDX, then an address
into RDI, and then we wrote that EDX value
to the address RDI points to.
Now look at the source code of the hello world
program.
Here the code said we move the string, “hell”
which is of course 4 bytes, into the variable
4.
And then store variable:4 in memory location
1.
And that is just another way of saying, we
move the string, or the 4 bytes, “hell”
into rdx.
And then we move rdx to a memory location
we specify in RDI.
Which memory location, and converting the
string “hell” to the four bytes is what
my compiler program does.
I know, maybe that is a bit too confusing,
maybe better just ignore my compiler shenanigans.
But if think about what we did.
We executed these few instructions that move
a value into some memory location.
And we did that by using super weird instructions,
which we usually refer to as “gadgets”.
To perform this memory write, we used three
gadgets.
First we used a “pop rdx, pop rbx” gadget,
then a “pop rdi” gadget and then a “mov
gadget”.
And see what all these gadgets have in common?
They all end with a return instruction.
Now bend you mind.
take what we just witnessed and try to fit
it into the concept of a machine executing
instructions.
First, we have memory, that is our stack.
On there we had all these addresses and values.
And in a weird fuckedup way the stack pointer
was our instruction pointer, right?
Our weird machine basically started with a
return opcode, which took the first address
on the stack and continued CPU execution there.
Then the stack pointer pointed to the next
value, we popped it and moved it to the next.
Pooped another value moved it to the next.
And then came another return which took the
value and let the CPU execute code there.
Moving the stack again to the next value.
So In a way those addresses on the stack,
when we have a return, define instruction
handlers, right?
You could say this address here is actually
the opcode, the instruction to perform a pop
rdx and then a pop rbx.
And this other gadget, this address here,
is the opcode for the move of edx into the
address of rdi.
Isn’t this basically the same thing how
a x86 assembler “call” instruction actually
means we push an address on the stack and
set the instruction pointer to the given destination.
How is that “call” x86 instruction different
from our weird machine gadget?
It isn’t!
Both define some action, what it does, and
then the machine moves to the next instruction.
The CPU does this by incrementing the instruction
pointer, the Java Virtual Machine does this
by simply incrementing the program counter,
and our weird machine does this by incrementing
the stack pointer.
I know, these gadgets are super weird instructions.
And each program, depending on how much code
it contains and what kind of functions were
written there, and where in the memory the
compiler places the code, changes what kind
of gadgets are available.
With the small tool ropgadgets we can actually
list all gadgets, so assembler snippets that
have this pattern of a few instructions followed
by a “ret”.
Basically these are all the weird instructions
that we can use to implement whatever we want
on this weird machine.
I know it’s crappy.
Nobody said that it has to be a well thought
out machine like the CPU or the Java Virtual
Machine.
But it’s enough to basically perform any
kind of computation.
It was enough for me to collect gadgets that
seemed useful and built a compiler that translates
this text representation to actual addresses
that point to those gadgets.
And that’s why each program with such a
vulnerability, accidentally crafts its own
weird machine.
Each vulnerable program will have it’s own
instruction set, it’s own collection of
gadgets.
And it’s own initialisation code that setups
that weird machine.
Basically the code that triggered our vulnerability
in the first place.
So writing such an exploit.
Is in essence the setting up and instantiation
of a weird machine by triggering the buffer
overflow.
And then we program that weird machine with
a rop-chain, a collection of gadgets chained
together that will be executed by our weird
machine, thanks to how the x86 “ret” instruction
together with the stack works.
And what we can program is just bound by our
creativity and availability of useful gadgets.
But if you have a large amount of gadgets
you can understand that you could implement
ANYTHING you want.
You just chain these small assembler snippets
together to build anything.
In an attack you usually try to create a remote
shell or something, but it could literally
be just a regular program.
Like I have created these rop-chains that
for example take two numbers as an input,
adds them together, and prints the result.
And that’s it.
That is return oriented programming explained
in a super confused way.
I know, this is maybe not the best ROP tutorial.
But there are so many “normal” tutorials,
that I just wanted to try something different
and I hope there are some of you where this
kind of different angle on the topic is mind
opening.
At least for me this was so mindblowing and
beautiful that, as you know, it became a slogan
for my channel.
Also I like to remind you to checkout the
papers and talks I have listed in the description.
Please read them even if you didn’t understand
this video.
They are maybe better, but certainly more
correct explaining this concept of weird machines
and exploit development.
Anyway… thanks for watching and maybe checkout
my Patreon and YouTube membership in the description.