In this episode we will have a look at format
level 1 from exploit-exercises protostar.
This class of vulnerability is weird, but
was mind blowing to me, when I first saw it.
So first of all...
What are format strings?
Probably the most known function in C is printf.
Printf prints formatted data to stdout.
In my “programming in C” video I have
used printf to print a name that a user can
supply.
The parameters for printf() are the following.
The first parameter is the so called “format
string”.
In that early video that was “Knock, knock.”
percentage ‘S’.
And as a second parameter we used argv[1].
Which contains a string.
So printf read the format string and found
the percentage ‘S’ which means, that at
this position belongs a string.
So it takes the first supplied variable, in
this case argv[1] and places the string there.
Format strings support a lot of different
types of variables, for example %d, which
is a signed decimal integer.
Or %x, to display a number in hex.
And you can do even more than that.
For example if you specify a number between
the percentage and the specifier you can tell
to what size it should be padded.
And you can for example prepend a 0 to that
number, to pad the result with zeroes.
Format string functions like that exist also
in other languages.
For example you can use pretty much the same
features in python.
Print.
A format string, with percentage and then
the variables afterwards with another percentage
sign.
Or better use the format function which has
a slightly different syntax.
But in the end it’s all the same.
And now you wonder.
How the hell can something, that just prints
text, be exploited?
So let’s have a look at the source code
of format level 1.
Main calls the function vuln with the string
from argv[1].
And that string is placed in printf.
And then we have a global variable target,
which is checked if it got modified.
So pretty similar to the early stack buffer
overflow challenges.
We need to manipulate this value.
But how can we manipulate a variable in memory
with printf?
Well.
Let’s do this step by step.
Let’s first execute the program.
As you can see, it will simply print whatever
we supply in argv[1].
That looks simple.
But there is one small thing you should notice.
Which parameter of the printf() does the attacker
control?...
It’s not the second parameter like in the
programming in C video.
It’s the first parameter.
The format string.
Soooo…
Can we just use some percentage syntax?
Let’s try.
Let’s enter a format string.
Test ‘%d’.
Oh damn.
it printed a number.
Weird.
Let’s add some more!
Woha. more numbers.
Let’s print them as hex instead of signed
decimal numbers.
That looks more familiar.
Remember the videos where we were looking
at the stack?
Do those values starting with bffff remind
you of something?
Those were stack addresses.
So what are we printing here?
If you have watched the previous episode about
reversing C, you know how functions are being
called.
Especially in 32bit.
The parameters are simply placed on to the
stack, and then the function is called.
So if you would use printf normally, your
variables that you want to print would be
placed on the stack.
Well now there are no variables being placed
on the stack, so what values are you reading?
Obviously you are reading whatever printf
can find on the stack.
So any value on the stack.
So what can you do with that?
First of all, it is a memory leak vulnerability.
You can leak all kinds of stuff from the stack.
Imagine you had a program with ASLR, meaning
that the location of the stack in memory is
random.
And you don’t know where it is, but you
need the address for a buffer overflow to
jump to shellcode.
With this here, you can leak values from the
process memory, more specifically from the
stack, and thus possibly leaking stack addresses.
Which can then be used in a second step for
a buffer overflow.
In a recent CTF which I played there was an
exploitable challenge where I used a format
string vulnerability to leak the stack canary.
I will do a video about exploit mitigations
at another point, but the stack canary is
a random value which protects from buffer
overflows.
If I can get this number, I can defeat this
protection.
Which I did.
So at first leaking som weird values from
a process memory doesn’t sound like much,
but there are many examples you could come
up with, where disclosing some memory could
help exploiting a target.
After all, bugs like heartbleed were “just”
leaking some memory and it was awful.
Ok but in our particular case.
How can we use that to modify a value.
At the moment it only looks like we can leak
values from the stack.
Let’s have a look at the printf manpage.
man 3 printf.
And let’s scroll to the well known BUGS
section.
It says here,
“if something comes from untrusted user
input, it may contain %n, causing the printf()
call to write to memory and creating a security
hole“
And a little bit further up the specifier
‘n’ is explained as:
n The number of characters written so far
is stored into the integer indicated by the
int * (or variant) pointer argument.
So percentage ‘n’ writes the amount of
characters that were already printed, into
a variable.
And a variable is just some area in memory.
And we know that to specify where that area
is, we need use a pointer.
Or if we just look at the assembler code,
a pointer is simply an address, so that printf
knows where to write the result.
So if you were to write a legit C program
with %n, you would place a pointer to an integer
variable as a parameter to printf, or in assembler
this would simply be putting the address of
the variable onto the stack.
This means, that whatever value is on the
stack, is used as a location where printf
will write to.
Now you can basically solve this challenge
alone.
We need to write a value in target.
So let’s use objdump -t to find all symbols
from this binary.
And here is the address of the target variable.
Now, when we want printf to write something
at this location, we have to find this address
on the stack.
Let’s start investigating.
I will use python and a one line script directly
from the commandline via -c to help me with
printing a test string.
For example 10 hex numbers.
Mh.
Maybe I want to seperate them.
Doesn’t look like the address is here.
Maybe if we print more values from the stack.
Nope.
Not here.
Maybe more?
Wait a minute.
What is that weird pattern.
From the values of those hex values it could
be ascii.
hex 20 is a space afterall.
With python we can quickly convert those hex
values to a ascii characters.
And wooohh..
%x?
That loooks like our string that we have supplied.
Let’s test that.
Let’s add some capital As, because we can
recognize those ascii values easily.
Now we just have to look for 4141414141.
And indeed.
there are our As.
And that makes sense.
Because the program arguments are simply stored
on the stack, like the environment variables
and other stuff.
Cool.
This means we can simply place the address
from the target on the stack ourselves, by
adding it to our string.
So get the address again for target, and then
we can add the address in our string.
Maybe wrap it in some As and Bs, so we can
find it in the output easily.
Uhhh. yes.
There it is.
cool!
So in theory, we just have to replace the
%x that was printing this address with %n
to instead write to this
address location.
You could do it more intelligently, but I
will just figure it out with trial and error.
You have to be careful, because remember from
our previous videos where the stack was shifting
around because of stuff like environment variables?
The different length program argument that
we supply, moves around the stack as well.
So you might have to fiddle around quite a
bit until you just get it right.
Ok that took a bit, but looks cool.
The last %x seems to reference our address
now.
And when we replace the x with the n, to write
to that address we modified the target.
And you can imagine, that if we can write
anywhere in memory, we could overwrite things
to redirect code execution as well.
So that will be the case in later levels.
Just a small tip for when you work on format
string exploits.
It makes sense to keep your attack string
always the same length.
Then you don’t have to fiddle around much.
Just use a python script that always extends
or cuts the string at like 500 characters
or something.
And then you have enough space to play around
and the stack doesn’t move around.