You should now be familiar with the stack
level 0 from protostar and especially our
quick look at what happens when you compile
this code on a modern system.
Specifically with the stack cookies.
In this video I wanna develop a working exploit
for it.
And believe me there are a few mountains we
have to overcome.
Let’s get everybody quickly on track.
We have a simple buffer overflow vulnerability.
Originally the goal was to overflow into another
variable to change the outcome of an if case.
But this is not possible anymore because the
buffer is now placed after the variable - not
before.
So to execute the if-case we want, we could
maybe overflow the return pointer on the stack
and simply redirect the code execution there.
But an issue that we face is the stack cookie
which contains three random bytes that are
checked before the function returns.
So in order to overflow the return pointer
we would have to guess the cookie.
This means we have to write an exploit which
executes the target over and over again, millions
of times always guessing a stack cookie, and
eventually we should get lucky.
But before we write that code, let’s first
develop the exploit as if we know the cookie
value.
This input really must be correct in order
to work once we guess the correct cookie value.
So we have to debug this heavily.
Let’s start by opening the binary in gdb
with the peda extension which makes it look
nicer and let’s just enter a loooot of characters
in order to observe what happens.
Oops stack smashing detected.
We obviously want to ignore that.
So let’s set a breakpoint just before it
would continue to __stack_chk_fail.
And then set eip to where it would have jumped
to if the cookie was correct.
With a simple commands directive we can automate
this everytime this breakpoint is hit.
Then continue.
Segmentation fault, that’s what we would
expect.
Awesome.
Oh…
Segmentation fault at the return?
Not segfault because we redirected code execution
to faulty memory?
Look at the stack register.
ESP points to invalid memory, so when the
return isntruction wants to look up the return
pointer on the stack it tries to follow where
esp points to, and that is obviously accessing
invalid memory.
Damn… how did we overwrite and modify the
stack pointer?
Let’s look again in the disassembly.
Down here just before the return.
So a value referenced by the base pointer,
so a value on the stack is moved into ecx.
And then ecx -4 is calculated and that becomes
the new stack pointer.
And when we look at the beginning of this
function, we can see that the stack pointer
-4 is stored in ecx and pushed on to the stack.
So the stack pointer is also saved on the
stack.
I think that’s another mitigation attempt,
because before we are able to control the
return pointer, we first have to control the
stack pointer.
At first this doesn’t seem to be an issue,
because this just means we have to write a
valid stack pointer and point it into the
buffer we control, and then the return will
take the return pointer we control in the
buffer esp points to and we win.
But the issue is this modern system also has
now ASLR.
We can see that if we re-enable aslr in the
debugger and run it a few times.
Observe the esp value.
It’s always different.
I admit it’s not fully random, but it’s
more bytes we would have to guess.
And to hit the cookie AND a valid stack address
is starting to look bad.
Let’s say we would know the base memory
of the stack, would that help us?
There is even more here.
Let’s rerun the program again, and this
time let’s see where esp points to and compare
it to where the stack actually starts in memory.
And when you do this a few times you can quickly
see, that esp varies quite a lot from where
the stack really starts.
In fact there is a huge gap with a random
size of just zeros between the start of the
stack we use in the code where esp points
to, and the environment variables that are
at the actual beginning of the stack memory
area.
I think this is another way to randomize values,
because ASLR would only randomize the upper
parts of an address and this way also the
lower bytes become unpredictable.
The game of exploitation has clearly changed.
There are more hurdles.
So does this mean now it’s game over?
It’s not exploitable anymore?
We can’t do it with a single input overflow?
Well.
there is a way.
But we have to get creative.
It’s not that easy anymore.
Ok so we know there is a cookie on the stack
and we believe it’s bruteforceable.
So let’s assume we found the correct cookie,
how do we go from there.
We know that a valid stack pointer is stored
after the cookie, right?
The value of esp was saved at the beginning
and restored here at the end again.
which means we can abuse that.
we don’t have to overwrite the whole pointer.
What if we just corrupt the first byte, so
the lowest part of the address.
Which means that the stack pointer stays valid
but suddenly points into a slightly different
stack memory.
And maybe we can make it slightly point into
the buffer we control, which is just a bit
lower than the stored esp value here.
So then we restore this slightly off value,
return can now follow the address as it points
into valid stack memory and take the address
there to return into.
And if it points into our buffer now, we can
control where we wanna return to, and we could
return into the if-case that prints our goal.
We can achieve that by writing enough data
to the buffer so that we fill up just short
off the stored stack pointer, and because
strings end with a zero byte in C, a null
will be written to the lowest part of the
stored esp value, thus make it a bit smaller,
and when we are lucky it points into our buffer.
Let’s figure out the length.
So when we run it with the long input, we
see that esp got overwritten with SSSS.
One byte is 4 lower than the others, thus
became an O, which was cauysed by the ecx-4.
So this means we want to stop right before
that.
And when we run it now, we see that esp ends
now in fc.
So it worked, because we predicted the lowest
part on the stack is overwritten with 0 and
because of ecx-4, so 0 - 4 we end up with
fc.
But as you can see, we didn’t get lucky,
esp points to not our buffer.
But let’s rerun it a few times and do the
same and at some point we will get lucky and
now esp points to our buffer.
And when we now return we actually return
into 4d4d4d4d, which is MMMM.
It worked.
Actually the randomization of the zero padding
on the stack makes this work, because at some
point the lowest randomized value of the address
will be just right, so that the 0 is the right
amount of change so esp points into our buffer.
But you also see it’s not 100% reliable.
We have to guess the cookie correct and then
hope that the esp randomization is also nice
to us.
But that’s fairly common so I hope that
it’s common enough to still make it feasible.
So now all that we have to do is, put it together.
Let’s write a quick python script.
We import struct to convert the address to
4 byte strings.
Little lambda helper function for that.
And then we simply make our exploit string
fill the buffer with mostly the address we
want to return to.
We hope we can make esp point into this area.
And then comes the Cookie value, which we
later have to write some bruteforce logic
for.
Afterwards then comes 4 more bytes, and that’s
it.
Then we print it.
Looks good.
You see the raw bytes are output with hexdump.
Write it to a file.
Let’s set a breakpoint at the cookie check
to make sure the cookie is in the right place.
And then we can use the file as input in gdb.
First breakpoint was the cookie check.
And we can see we overwrite the cookie with
COOK.
Now when I press continue the other breakpoint
from before will hit and skip tghe cookie
check and we reach the return.
Oh and look at that.
We got lucky with esp and esp actually points
into our buffer.
When we now continue we return into the if-case
that prints the modified string.
And there it is.
Amazing!
So the exploit theoretically works.
All that is left, is the cookie bruteforcing.
Unfortunately that deserves it’s own episode
again.
It’s just programming, but doing it you
can learn a lot about linux and I don’t
wanna squeeze it in here.
Again, try to do that part yourself.
You could really learn alot.