Last video we have explored a format string
vulnerability from the protostar examples,
but had it compiled on a modern system with
ASLR and 64bit.
At first I thought we couldn’t solve it
but explored some tricks and played around
with it, but then actually figured out a reliable
technique.
So let’s explore some more of the format
levels.
Format1, at first, looks very simple.
Remember last time we just failed because
it required that we write to target the exact
value 0xdeadbeef, and here we just have to
write..
Something?
Let’s have quick look if our trick still
works.
So this level also takes an argument, but
passes it directly to printf.
No sprintf and buffer involved.
Anyway.
we compile it again on our 64bit ubuntu version
and open it in gdb.
Then we set a breakpoint at the if compare
of target, run it and as arguments we use
AAAAAAAAAA.
Then we have a look at the stack.
See how our As don’t show up?
Where are they?
Let’s keep looking further down.
Oh wow.
They are all the way down there.
And what’s all this stuff again?
Well so.
See, we didn’t copy our string input to
a local variable like buffer did in the last
challenge.
We directly print the arguments.
And the arguments are placed, along with the
environment variables all the way at the start
of the stack.
So these are the environment variables.
And you see, there is no stack address we
could overwrite and abuse like we did last
level.
That sucks.
But actually it’s still solveable, we don’t
need the trick from last video at all.
It’s simpler than you might think.
But let’s explore that with the next challenge,
format2, that one we haven’t looked at yet
and boils down to the same thing.
Looks a bit more promising, right?
It does read data into a local variable on
the stack.
But it doesn’t look like we can overflow
the buffer.
This program gets the input from standard
input instead of an argument.
And then later target is checked if it’s
64.
Ok.
So let’s compile it and open it in gdb.
Again we look for the if-compare, seems to
be here, 0x40 is 64.
And set a breakpoint then run it.
This time it’s waiting for input, so enter
some As and Bs.
Now we hit the breakpoint and let’s have
a look at the stack.
Mh, we know that our buffer has 512 bytes,
and looks like there are a loot of stack addresses
in range.
But why is that, isn’t the 512 bytes buffer
unallocated or empty?
Well no not really.
You see it’s a local variable on the stack,
which means it simply moved the stack pointer
further up to make space for it, but doesn’t
clear it.
So these are leftover values from other functions
that ran before and had a stack there, which
then got destroyed again when they returned,
but their values always remain there.
For regular program execution that doesn’t
really matter, except that you must not expect
a variable to be initialised with zeros, because
you can have bad luck and something was in
it’s place before.
Anyway.
Let’s see where our target variable is.
We can use print and then ampercant target
to get a pointer, so basically the address
of target.
But what is that?
That doesn’t look like a stack address?
Somebody who has some experience with exploitation
on 64bit knows already what that is.
It’s a very recognisable address.
With vmmap you can check the virtual memory
and see that it’s part of our binary?
Look at the permissions for this memory region.
It is read and writeable, not executable.
So it’s not where code is.
It’s in a data segment.
And when we look at the code we see that target
isn’t defined in a function as local variable.
It’s a global variable, so it’s placed
in a data segment.
Now if you have some experience with exploitation
64bit targets, you also know that that means,
this address is not affected by ASLR by default.
Lets add another printf here, like we did
last video to print the address of target.
And when we run it a few times, you see target
doesn’t change.
Awesome!
So it should be fairly straight forward.
Step 1: let’s find our input on the stack.
We enter some As followed by %x to print stack
values.
And here we are.
1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6.
At offset 6 we have our input.
So we could place our address there instead
of the As, and then replace the 6th %x with
the %n to write to it.
Let’s try it.
So we should now enter our input via echo,
so we can encode raw characters in hex.
Then pipe the input into format2.
So let’s enter the address of target.
Ah see, there it is, but it’s 4 bytes, so
there is also a space still included.
This has to be a zero, because the address
is only 3 bytes.
So we add that, but now we don’t see any
output anymore.
What happened?
Well, printf prints strings.
And strings are null-terminated in C. So printf
stops when it reahed the 0.
So we never reach our %x format modifiers.
This means, we should move our address to
the end, so we can have format stuff before.
Now let’s try to find again our address.
This time I’m using the dollar syntax to
enter an offset directly.
So we know our start was at offset 6, so the
address has to be further down.
Also don’t forget to escape the dollar here
on the commandline, because dollar is a special
charachter for the shell.
If we keep going with the offsets, we can
find the As.
Now sometimes the offset might not be right,
so maybe you have to add or remove a few characters
as padding to align it perfectly.
Ok now looks good.
Let’s change it to a %n.
Segmentation fault.
Well that didn’t work.
Weird.
Let’s write our input to a file, open gdb,
and use that file as input to investigate
the crash.
So here we are at a move.
It tries to move whatever is in r15d into
the address in rax.
And so rax appears to be an invalid address.
It’s not our target.
There is a 0xa.
And that is obviously a newline.
So that’s the issue.
We are on 64bit, so we have 64bit addresses.
But we only entered 4 bytes, and after the
echo is a newline.
So we just have to add 4 more nullbytes.
Ok we don’t get a crash now.
But target is still 0.
How is that?
Let’s make it crash again by making the
address invalid again.
This way we should be able to investigate
if our address would be correct and what is
written to it.
So we see, rax looks good.
It only is invalid because of what we changed.
Otherwise it would be great.
And so it tries to write r15d to it, and that
is, 0?
What?
Shouldn’t %n write the amount of characters
already printed?
Let’s think for a second.
Ohhhhhh.
Of course it’s 0.
Because we didn’t pint anything yet.
Before we do the %n we obviously have to print
something first.
So let’s add %64d, to print 64 characters.
Now that’s 4 characters long, this means
we shifted everything by 4, and in order to
lign up everything again, that the address
is at the correct offset, we have to subtract
4 characters somewhere.
But luckily we made the padding earlier large
enough and so that’s simple.
And here we go, it’s “you modified the
target”.
FINALLYYY finally we managed to exploit a
simple example on a modern system without
much hassle.
Goddamit.
So maybe now you wonder, but the system has
ASLR, why is this address fixed.
Well, the system has aslr, and the system
libraries like libc are affected by aslr,
you can see that when you use ldd to print
the library dependencies of the binary, it
keeps changing.
But the binary itself is not affected by ASLR.
Unless we specifically compile it to be position
independent code.
And wie can do that with the -pie flag for
position independent executable and -fPIC
for position independent code.
If we now execute format2 and check the address
of target, then we see it keeps changing a
lot.
Now it’s going to be much harder.
Maybe with some strategies from the last video
it’s doable.
I leave that as an exercise to you watching.